[
  {
    "chapter": "C3 Quantitative Chemistry",
    "question": "What is a limiting rectant?",
    "id": "2d01a58c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A reactant that does not have enough mass to react with all the product"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Do positive ions move to the anode or the cathode?",
    "id": "310ab768-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Cathode"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "How does higher light intensity affect the rate of photosynthesis?",
    "id": "2e401780-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Increase"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "In this reaction, what has been oxidised and what has been reduced? K + Na^+^ = K^+^ + Na",
    "id": "30fda5fa-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "K has been oxidized, Na^+^ has been reduced"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Suggest a possible challenge in buying lands to restrict deforestation.",
    "id": "3eaf0644-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Resistance from businesses to maintain profit or demand / Money needed"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "What is a polymer?",
    "id": "287fd290-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Millions of small molecules joined together in a chain to form a large molecule"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Which organ breaks down alcohol before it causes permanent damage?",
    "id": "27f3da24-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Liver"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "What is the name of extra small DNA rings found in some prokaryotes?",
    "id": "1e83da7a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Plasmid"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "How is malaria spread?",
    "id": "2ca81e2c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "By female Anopheles mosquitoes"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "Who came up with the Plumb Pudding model of the atom",
    "id": "3532fc24-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "J J Thompson"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "What happens to the long wave radiation that is reemitted from the Earth in the atmosphere?",
    "id": "3ee6d772-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "It is absorbed by the greenhouse gases"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "What is quantitative sampling?",
    "id": "3be2d472-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A technique to record and estimate the number of organisms in a particular area"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name two types of effectors.",
    "id": "3409df34-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Muscle; Glands"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What is the function of a gene?",
    "id": "36ae234e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "To code for a particular sequence of amino acids in order to make a specific protein."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "Why are gamma rays used in medical treatment?",
    "id": "3bb9bb8c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Can kill cancer cells"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "State the units of density",
    "id": "31df4fdc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "kg/m3"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Which type of reproduction is based only on mitosis?",
    "id": "1f24b058-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Asexual"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Large flowers are a feature to help compete for...?",
    "id": "3c086430-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "(attract) Pollinators"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State the function of the ribcage.",
    "id": "25982bfe-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Protect the heart and lungs"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What are the two main disadvantages of using electrolysis to extract metals?",
    "id": "3164bb6e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Requires a large amount of energy to melt the compounds and to produce the necessary electricity"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What will be the products for the electrolysis of molten iron bromide?",
    "id": "315cdcbe-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Iron and bromine"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What is an elastic potential store?",
    "id": "223bd758-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Energy stored in an object which has been stretched or compressed."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What is a weak acid?",
    "id": "30bab344-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "An acid which will have some molecules which do not split up into their ions. E.g. in ethanoic acid only some of the molecules will have split up into the ethanoate ion and H_ ions."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "How does malaria affect the body?",
    "id": "2caab416-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Damages blood and liver cells"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "What is a parallel circuit?",
    "id": "2de7e862-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A circuit with more than one route for charge to flow"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "Approximately how many elements are there?",
    "id": "35065a3e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "100"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "Describe the Plumb Pudding model of the atom",
    "id": "35354a60-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A ball of positive charge with negative electrons embedded in it"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "What is combustion?",
    "id": "398ac8ba-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The reaction of a fuel with oxygen"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C3 Quantitative Chemistry",
    "question": "What symbol do we use for relative formula mass?",
    "id": "2cf588a6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Mr"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Define 'biodiversity'.",
    "id": "3cf742f8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A measure of the variety of all the different species of organisms within an ecosystem"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C8 Chemical Analysis",
    "question": "Describe the melting and boiling points of pure substances",
    "id": "39ae285a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "One very specific temperature"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Are power stations par of the national grid?",
    "id": "2e27bece-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "no"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "When an object is heated the transfer pathway is…?",
    "id": "221f5c18-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Heating"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "What is the major way in which plants lose water in hot, dry conditions?",
    "id": "3cab7850-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Transpiration"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "What is the unit of work done?",
    "id": "29db8bca-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Joules (J)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "What is the unit for power?",
    "id": "2e02fd8c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Watts (W)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "How is pH measured?",
    "id": "30c4db58-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "pH is related to the concentration of H^+^ in a solution."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "Calculate the average mass of Cu, when 70% of the atoms are 63Cu and 30% are 65Cu",
    "id": "1f8d99b0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "63.6"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "State a difference between animal cells and bacteria.",
    "id": "1e88c436-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A: No cell wall and plasmid, linear DNA; B: Cell wall and plasmid, circular DNA"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Suggest a possible challenge in reintroducing hedgerows.",
    "id": "3eac564c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Loss of land available for growing crops (less profit)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Name the situation where a body of water has low oxygen levels, leading to marine organisms' death.",
    "id": "3e081802-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Eutrophication"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C10 Using resources",
    "question": "What is sustainable development?",
    "id": "400df77a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Development that meets the needs of the current generations without compromising the ability of future generations to meet their own needs"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C10 Using resources",
    "question": "How is bioleaching carried out?",
    "id": "4037f6c4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Bacteria are used to produce a leachate solution"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "What is the name for a substance made of billions of oppositely charged ions joined together?",
    "id": "28308a6e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Giant ionic lattice"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "What is another name for photosynthetic cells in plants?",
    "id": "1ea75748-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Palisade mesophyll cells"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "State the rule for resistance in a series circuit",
    "id": "2db737c6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "the more resistors, the greater the resistance. RT=R1+R2"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "How did the world's oceans form?",
    "id": "3ecf8446-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The Earth's temperature cooled, causing water vapour in the air to condense"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "How does carbon from plants get into animals?",
    "id": "3ceaed46-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Feeding/Eating"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "What charge will an ion of oxygen take?",
    "id": "2814dddc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "2- (6 electrons in outer shell so needs to gain two)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "State the equation which links gravitaional field strength, mass and weight",
    "id": "29c294f8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "W=mg"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "What will absorb (stop) gamma radiation?",
    "id": "36648158-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "several centimetres of lead"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Is cystic fibrosis a dominant or recessive condition?",
    "id": "37d9d740-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Recessive."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What is variation within a population?",
    "id": "37e7a686-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Differences in the characteristics of individuals in a population."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "State the equation which links current, potential difference and resistance",
    "id": "2dec9e5c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "V=IR"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Give a reason for alloying a metal",
    "id": "298bdad0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "To make it harder, to make it less reactive"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "The flow of blood in veins relies on what?",
    "id": "255c76f4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Skeletal muscle contraction"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C10 Using resources",
    "question": "Given an example of a product that can be recycled",
    "id": "4049159e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Metal"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Define 'adult stem cells'.",
    "id": "1f389884-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Stem cells that can only differentiate into a specific type of cell"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "What is the unit of force?",
    "id": "29ddfeb4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Newtons (N)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Which ions are in (NH~4~)~2~O",
    "id": "30d2fd5a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "2 ions of NH__ and one O__"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State the importance of the neutralising role bile has.",
    "id": "25399e90-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Small intestine does not have protective mucus layer + Enzymes will denature in small intestine"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name a drug that reduces blood cholesterol levels.",
    "id": "2582110c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Statins"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What causes antibiotic resistance?",
    "id": "382befe4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Random mutations in bacteria/Bacteria sharing resistant genes"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "Define specific heat capacity",
    "id": "22982364-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The energy needed to raise the temperature 1 kg of a material by 1_C"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Where is the cell body found in the sensory neurone?",
    "id": "340e6162-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Along/On the neurone fibre"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What are some disadvantages of biofuels?",
    "id": "226b9fec-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "production of fuel can damage ecosystems and reduce variety of crops grown"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "The potential difference between the live wire and others in the plug is _____ V",
    "id": "2dce7b52-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "230V"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "Explain why increasing the temperature increases the rate of reaction",
    "id": "34d6d89a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Increases the speed at which particles move therefore more frequent collisions. Increases the number of particles which have the activation energy therefore more collisions result in a reaction."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "What is an induced magnet?",
    "id": "407f6964-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A magnetic material which becomes a magnet when placed in a magnetic field."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "A reaction is exothermic in the forward direction. What will occur if the temperature is increased?",
    "id": "34f0aa86-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The backward reaction will increase as it is endothermic and will reduce the temperature"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "Define weight",
    "id": "29aeee12-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The force ofgravity acting on an object's mass"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "How do viruses make you ill?",
    "id": "2c598a46-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Produce inside body cells, causing damage"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "State a difference between quantitative sampling and transect sampling.",
    "id": "3be7c9c8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Quantitative sampling takes samples at random coordinates; Transect sampling takes samples at specific intervals along the line (not random)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "How is information passed through the synapse?",
    "id": "34214a2a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Neurotransmitters/Chemicals are released, which travel across the synapse to the receptor sites on the next neurone"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C8 Chemical Analysis",
    "question": "What does a substance's Rf value depend on?",
    "id": "3abf04c6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "How soluble it is in the solvent"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Briefly describe the third stage in the cell cycle.",
    "id": "1f2eb51c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Cytoplasm and cell membrane divides into two daughter cells"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "How many electrons are in a Neon atom?",
    "id": "1fa6b6de-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "10"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Define 'tumour'.",
    "id": "27cd03cc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A mass of cells grown abnormally (uncontrollable growth)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "How does a change in pH affect enzyme structure?",
    "id": "24f9268a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "pH change affects forces holding enzyme structure together, causing it to denature"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "What is a reversible reaction?",
    "id": "34dde414-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A reaction which can go from reactants to products but also from products to reactants"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Name a substance that diffuses into our cells for use.",
    "id": "1ec3b2b2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Oxygen, glucose"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What is the name of the energy transfer pathway by waves?",
    "id": "2217f810-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Radiating"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C5 Energy Changes",
    "question": "Is breaking bonds endothermic or exothermic?",
    "id": "319eaa0e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Endothermic. Chemical bonds are strong so require energy to break (like when you have to put energy in to separate magnets from each other)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What is the name of the process in which the nuclei of atoms fuse together?",
    "id": "224d6fd6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "fusion"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "If something has lost electrons, what charge will it have?",
    "id": "2812675a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Positive (because they have lost a negative!)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "What is crude oil?",
    "id": "3960e914-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A mixture of hydrocarbons"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Within a population, there is normally very little genetic variation – true or false?",
    "id": "37e9ebe4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "False – just look around you at humans!"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "Name the first four alkanes",
    "id": "397136ac-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Methane, ethane, propane, butane"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Define 'dilute'.",
    "id": "1ecddc9c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A solution with a high water conc, but low solute conc"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Draw the circuit symbol for a cell",
    "id": "2d13a782-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "What are the two possible units for rate of reaction?",
    "id": "34ba7fba-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "g/s or cm_/s (where s is seconds)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "How does wind or air flow affect rate of transpiration?",
    "id": "27bb66c6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "More wind increases rate (as maintains steep conc gradient)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "State the three common acids and give their formulae",
    "id": "308b4686-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Hydrochloric acid, HCl(aq), Sulphuric acid, H_SO_(aq), Nitric acid, HNO_"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Describe the flow of blood as atria of the heart contract.",
    "id": "2575b39e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Blood flows from atria down to ventricles"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "Sketch the Force (y) -Extension (x) curve for stretching a spring from no force to beyond its elastic limit.",
    "id": "29f6d7b8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State the importance of having proteins in our diet.",
    "id": "24c3e326-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Structural components/Hormones/Antibodies/Enzymes"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name the main female reproductive hormone.",
    "id": "3460bce6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Oestrogen"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "What are the units of momentum?",
    "id": "29ecf6c6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "kilogram metres per second (kg m/s)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What does the term “dominant” mean?",
    "id": "36b9a9c6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The individual only needs one copy of this allele for its phenotype to be seen."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "On a distance time graph a upward curve represents…",
    "id": "2a1efb1c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "acceleration"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "Where does photosynthesis occur in the cell?",
    "id": "2e368db4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Chloroplast"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What are criterias for decay to occur?",
    "id": "3814ec7c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Oxygen, bacteria (decomposers), correct temperature"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "Is photosynthesis endothermic or exothermic?",
    "id": "2e31aa60-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Endothermic"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "If a cell is in a hypertonic solution, water will ___ (enter/leave) the cell.",
    "id": "1edcb050-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Leave"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "How many divisions do a cell undergo in meiosis?",
    "id": "368ea91a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Twice"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What are some disadvantages of solar power?",
    "id": "22895974-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "unreliable - no electricity produced at night and limited on cloudy days. Expensive to construct."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name the main male reproductive hormone.",
    "id": "346eda24-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Testosterone"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "State a function of liver.",
    "id": "3064c362-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Detoxification / Breakdown of old blood cells / Remove lactic acid (convert to glucose)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What is the formula of sodium sulphate?",
    "id": "30e05770-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Na_SO_"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "What colour is the earth wire in a three core cable?",
    "id": "2dc56062-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "green and yellow"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "What are the three things that animals compete for?",
    "id": "3bea4536-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Food, mates, territory"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "What is stored in camels' humps and what is it for?",
    "id": "3ca4101a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Fat store --> can be metabolised to make water"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "How is the amount of product changing at equilibrium?",
    "id": "34ec003a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "It is not changing"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "What are the risks of exposure of X-rays?",
    "id": "3bbec712-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "X-rays are ionising so can cause mutations which may result in cancer"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Name a chemical that gets built up in organisms in bioaccumulation.",
    "id": "3e0f4cc6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Heavy metals/Fertiliers/Pesticides/Herbicides"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "Does a sound wave travel faster in water or air?",
    "id": "3b19fd04-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "water"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "Earth's early atmosphere was similar to Venus and Mars, what do their atmosphere's consist of?",
    "id": "3ebf1ac0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Carbon dioxide with little or no oxygen"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "Name a fungal disease in humans.",
    "id": "2c9de4ca-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Athlete's foot"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Name the substance found in xylem cells that allows the cells to withstand high water pressure.",
    "id": "1eafc748-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Lignin"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What is the genotype of a female?",
    "id": "37cba6ac-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "XX"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "A disease causes large areas of trees to die. Is their death cause by an abiotic or biotic factor?",
    "id": "3bd5e6fe-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Biotic (as diseases are caused by pathogens, which are living beings)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Which focus knob should be used during high power magnification?",
    "id": "1e50c4be-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Fine focus knob"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C10 Using resources",
    "question": "What needs to be removed from industrial waste water?",
    "id": "4028b95c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Organic matter and harmful chemicals"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "The genetic material in the nucleus of a cell is….",
    "id": "36a4222c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "DNA"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name a chemical method of contraception.",
    "id": "34872868-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Spermicides"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Where do you get stem cells in plants?",
    "id": "1f54b884-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Meristem/Root tip/Shoot tip"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What controls the opening and closing of stomata?",
    "id": "27ac797c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Guard cells"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "Give one use of X-rays.",
    "id": "3bb227aa-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Medical imaging"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What is produced at the anode in electrolysis of solutions?",
    "id": "31747324-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Either a halogen or oxygen (when there is no halogen present)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "How are the electrons arranged in atoms?",
    "id": "1f900fd8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Orbiting the nucleus in shells"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What is a gene?",
    "id": "36abcb12-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A small section of DNA on a chromosome."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "State the rule for current in a parallel circuit",
    "id": "2db99c00-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "the total current through the whole circuit is the sum of the currents through the separate components"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Define a displacement reaction",
    "id": "3077d22c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A reaction in which a more reactive element takes the place of a less reactive element in one of its compounds or in solution"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "What biological consequences does climate change bring about?",
    "id": "3e56a1f2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Changes in migration pattenrs and species distribution"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "If ionisation happens in DNA it can cause ___________ which may result in ____________",
    "id": "3522acca-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "mutations, cancer"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the upper chambers of the heart.",
    "id": "25694550-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Atria"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "How do you measure pH?",
    "id": "3092aa70-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "With an indicator or pH probe."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What elements make up lipids?",
    "id": "24befd02-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "C, H, O"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "What is the function of flagella?",
    "id": "1e865070-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "To allow the cell to swim and move around"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What is the formula of magnesium fluoride?",
    "id": "30ddad36-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "MgF_"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "What is the name given to the process that warms of the surface of the Earth",
    "id": "3ee94fb6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The greenhouse effect"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "State a difference in structure between xylem and phloem.",
    "id": "1eb22ad8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "X: dead, hollow tube, has lignin; P: living, has sieve plates, no lignin"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "What charge do electrons have?",
    "id": "28035da0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "-1"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "Name an example of a longitudinal wave",
    "id": "3ad6fc66-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Sound"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Name the gametes in animals.",
    "id": "36981ebe-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Sperm + Egg"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "What did Jame Chadwick discover about the atom?",
    "id": "36403afa-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "That the nucleus contains neutrons as well as protons"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Define 'zygote'.",
    "id": "1f4573a6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The single new cell formed right after fusion of gametes(sperm and egg)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Define 'enzyme'.",
    "id": "24e175c6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Biological catalysts that speed up chemical reactions"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Which objective lens should we start using?",
    "id": "1e4b914c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Low power objective lens"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name a method to cure type 1 diabetes.",
    "id": "344adb2e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Pancreas or pancreatic cell transplant"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "Work is done when an object is ….",
    "id": "29bb2f2e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "… moved through a distance"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "Who discovered that electrons are located in energy levels?",
    "id": "363de07a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Niels Bohr"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What is a neutral solution?",
    "id": "30900eb4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A solution with a pH of 7. Water is an example."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "State one difference between asexual and sexual reproduction.",
    "id": "36854ca8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A: no fertilisation/genetically identical offspring; S: fertilisation/genetic variation"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "If a reaction is exothermic in the forward direction what will it be in the reverse direction?",
    "id": "34e2ed7e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Endothermic"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "State the rule for potential difference in a series circuit",
    "id": "2db4f920-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "the total potential difference of the power supply is shared between components"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "State the rule for current in a series circuit",
    "id": "2db2b9b2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "the current is the same at every point in the circuit and in every component"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the product of the breakdown of starch.",
    "id": "250357e0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Simple sugars"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C8 Chemical Analysis",
    "question": "How is the Rf value calculated?",
    "id": "3abcbd10-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "distance moved by spot/distance moved by solvent"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "What is the formula for a mean rate of reaction in terms of products?",
    "id": "34b5cb32-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "quantity of reactant product formed/time taken"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C8 Chemical Analysis",
    "question": "How can chromatography show the difference between pure and impure substances?",
    "id": "3aba6ccc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Pure ones will not separate into a number of spots"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State the the function of the pancreas.",
    "id": "22b0e494-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Produces/Releases digestive enzymes"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "State the function of a neurone.",
    "id": "33fd361c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Transmit electrical impulses"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Why do enzymes stop working past their optimum temperature?",
    "id": "24f4533a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Denatured (substrate can no longer bind to active site)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "What is the unit of wave speed?",
    "id": "3b03c818-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "metres per second (m/s)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "State the function of the cell membrane.",
    "id": "1e5eb542-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Controls what substances go in and out of the cell"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "An object is said to _________ radiation when energy from an EM wave is taken up by the object",
    "id": "3ae8e80e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "absorb"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Describe the five steps of fossilisation by mineralisation.",
    "id": "38172fa0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "1. Organism dies and falls to the ground; 2. Flesh decays, leaving the skeleton behind; 3. Bones are covered in sand/soil; 4. Bones become mineralised and turns into rock (fossil); 5. Rock with fossil emerges due to geological movement (eg. earthquake) and erosion occurs to reveal fossil"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "A rock at the top of a hill is a store of ___________ energy.",
    "id": "22395f96-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "gravitational potential"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What is selective breeding?",
    "id": "37f88ae6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The process by which humans breed plants and animals for particular genetic characteristics."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Why can bacteria evolve quicker than other organisms?",
    "id": "3830878e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Because bacteria can reproduce at a quick rate"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "State the equation which links energy transferred, power and time",
    "id": "2df3dcbc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "E=Pt"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "What does insoluble mean?",
    "id": "284e5c38-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Does not dissolve in water"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Suggest 3 methods to prevent and slow down the development of antibiotic-resistant strains.",
    "id": "3832dc50-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "1. Do not overuse antibiotics; 2. Patients finish antibiotic course every time; 3. Restrict agricultural use of antibiotics"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Is this process oxidation or reduction? Na^+^ + e^-^ = Na",
    "id": "30e84b74-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Reduction"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "Name the toxic substance produced by anaerobic respiration.",
    "id": "2e630bd2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Lactic acid"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Owls' sharp hearing is an adaptation to compete for...?",
    "id": "3bf96674-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Food"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "How can the distribution of a species be measured?",
    "id": "3be54edc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Sampling along a transect"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Where is the relay neurone found in a reflex arc?",
    "id": "3419fb1c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Spinal cord"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "On a velocity time graph a downwards straight line represents …",
    "id": "2a2bbfc8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "decelleration"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "New drugs are tested extensively for three factors. Name the three factors.",
    "id": "2cdc7960-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Toxicity, efficacy, dose"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the tube that carries food from the mouth to the stomach.",
    "id": "22a46c6e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Oesophagus/Gullet"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "What two words describe the magnetic field within the coil of a solenoid?",
    "id": "409da078-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "strong and uniform"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "Name the three subatomic particles",
    "id": "1f6bb48a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Protons, neutrons, electrons"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "In terms of electrons, what do group 7 elements have in common?",
    "id": "1fb6df64-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "7 electrons in the outer shell"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "When the force moving an object is balanced by frictional forces it is moving at its _____________ _____________",
    "id": "2a19ea8c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "terminal velocity"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "When a conductor carrying a current is placed in a magnetic field, the magnet and the conductor ….",
    "id": "40b19c36-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "exert an equal and opposit force on one another"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "Define radioactive decay",
    "id": "350b110a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "An unstable nucleus changes to become more stabe and gives out radiation"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Current flows out of an appliance through the ______ wire",
    "id": "2dd306ea-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "neutral"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "State three biotic factors.",
    "id": "3bddd2f6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "New pathogens, new predators, new competitors, food availability"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "What is meant by a stable community?",
    "id": "3bd35a38-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Where all the species and environmental factors are in balance, hence population sizes remain fairly constant"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Name the organ that produces egg cells.",
    "id": "368a0fae-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Ovaries"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "What is the ionising power of gamma radiation?",
    "id": "366b8732-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "low"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "What does a step up transformer do?",
    "id": "2e2a1fd4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Increases p.d."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What are the units of mass?",
    "id": "21f13c02-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "kilograms"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What is the formula of iron (III) oxide?",
    "id": "30daf1fe-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Fe_O_"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name the cell type that detects stimuli in the internal or external environment.",
    "id": "33f63eb6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Receptor"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C5 Energy Changes",
    "question": "What is an endothermic reaction?",
    "id": "3185b850-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A reaction where energy is transferred from the surroundings."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What are some advantages of geothermal energy?",
    "id": "2277ec16-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "doesn't damage ecosystems, reliable."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "What does molten mean?",
    "id": "2841f0a6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Melted"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Which specialised cell in plants make up the tissue for transporting water?",
    "id": "1ead46bc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Xylem cells"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "On a velocity time graph a horizontal line represents …",
    "id": "2a2e342e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "constant speed"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Describe the I-V characteristic of a diode",
    "id": "2e14bec8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The current only flows through the diode in one direction, there is a very high resistance in the reverse direction."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "What did John Dalton contribute to our understanding of atomic theory?",
    "id": "3642a70e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Matter is made up of descrete, spherical particles, known as atoms"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Some bacteria have an extra layer on top of their cell walls. What is the name of that layer?",
    "id": "1e7c7ae6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Slime capsule"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "How does carbon from plants and animals get formed into rocks?",
    "id": "3cefe3be-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Fossilisation"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "The center of mas of an object is…",
    "id": "29b66890-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "the single point at which the objects weight appears to act."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C8 Chemical Analysis",
    "question": "How can pure substances be distinguished from impure ones?",
    "id": "39abdd98-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "By their melting/boiling points"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C3 Quantitative Chemistry",
    "question": "If the amount of solute in a solution is increased, what happens to its concentration?",
    "id": "2d0902fa-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Increases"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Which ions do the common acids form in solution?",
    "id": "308d91ca-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "HCl forms H_ and Cl_, H_SO_ forms 2H_ and SO___, HNO_ forms H_ and NO__"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "How do you test for an alkene?",
    "id": "399fdd4a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "React it with bromine water"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "How many pairs of chromosomes does an ordinary human body cell have?",
    "id": "37c6d780-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "23"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the products of the breakdown of lipids.",
    "id": "250fb95e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Glycerol and fatty acids"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "What is the mass of each subatomic particle?",
    "id": "364c11f4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "proton 1, neutron 1, elecrton ≈ 0"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Making full reference to structure and bonding in graphite, explain how it conducts electricity",
    "id": "2869278e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Each carbon has 3 bonds, 1 electron is delocalised, free to carry charge through the graphite"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Explain why methane has a low melting point",
    "id": "287d5736-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "It is a simple molecular substance with weak forces between the molecules (which are easy to break)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "Increasing temperature ______________ pressure in a gas if volume is constant",
    "id": "31da45f0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "increases"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "The internal energy store is…",
    "id": "22434e66-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "energy stored in the movement of particles."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "An example of direct current is…",
    "id": "2e1e7b84-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "batteries"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Draw the circuit symbol for a fuse",
    "id": "2d2546fe-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Balance this ionic equation: Mg^2+^ + Na = Na^+^ + Mg",
    "id": "30f32490-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Mg^2+^ + 2Na = 2Na^+^ + Mg"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Tigers urinating on trees is a behaviour adaptation to compete for...?",
    "id": "3bf4675a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Territory"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What are the units of power?",
    "id": "21fe4532-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Watts"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "What did Bohr's experiments show?",
    "id": "1f8628b0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "That electrons are in specific shells"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "State the function of the chloroplasts.",
    "id": "1e689cc4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Contain chlorophyll, absorb light to do photosynthesis"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "In this reaction, what has been oxidised and what has been reduced? Mg^2+^ + 2Na = 2Na^+^ + Mg",
    "id": "30f86414-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Na has been oxidised, Mg^2+^ has been reduced"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Which hormone stimulates the release of oestrogen?",
    "id": "347b77a2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "FSH"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "How do catalysts speed up reactions?",
    "id": "34db8d5e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "They provide another route for the reaction to take place which has a lower activation energy."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "What is the plum pudding model of the atom?",
    "id": "1f7567c8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A ball of positive charge with negative electrons studded into it"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State an effect of smoking on fetuses.",
    "id": "27e98cea-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Premature birth/Low birthweight/Stillbirth"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What is a nuclear energy store?",
    "id": "224aee0a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Energy stored in the nuclei of atoms that can fuse or split."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C10 Using resources",
    "question": "What is a life cycle assessment?",
    "id": "403e4222-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A way of assessing the environmental impact of a product across its entire life cycle"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C8 Chemical Analysis",
    "question": "What is chemical analysis?",
    "id": "39a4cfd0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The process of establishing what chemicals are present in a substance"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Define 'ecosystem'.",
    "id": "3bc65fc2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The interaction of a community with the abiotic parts of the environment"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Describe the main features of metals in terms of their structure",
    "id": "288248ae-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Positive metal ions arranged in layers with delocalised electrons"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What is emulsification?",
    "id": "25322fac-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Physically breaking down large oil drops into smaller droplets, increasing surface area for lipases to work on"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "Give three ways of increasing the force of a motor.",
    "id": "40b72958-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Increase the number of coils of wire, increase the strength of the magnetic field, increase the current"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "How could you measure the rate of a reaction from a graph?",
    "id": "34bcd774-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Draw a tangent to the curve and calculate the gradient."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "State the function of the cell wall.",
    "id": "1e661bc0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Strengthens the cell, provide support"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the lower chambers of the heart.",
    "id": "256bbba0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Ventricles"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "In Flemming's LH rule, the first finger gives the direction of …",
    "id": "40aeefae-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Magnetic Field"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "Name the change of state when a liquid becomes a solid",
    "id": "31ab64b0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "freezing"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the vessels that supply oxygen to the heart muscles.",
    "id": "25646c60-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Coronary arteries"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "The energy stored inside a system by the particles which make it up is known as ____________ energy",
    "id": "31c27ff6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "internal"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "How are plant roots adapted for efficient water and mineral absoprtion?",
    "id": "1f0d9d64-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Large SA (root hairs), transpiration stream"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "State four sources of land pollution.",
    "id": "3dfc34a6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Human sewage + Household wastes + Industrial wastes + Pesticides and herbicides in farming"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name the hormone that increases blood glucose level.",
    "id": "3432c642-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Glucagon"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "State the relative charges of the subatomic particles",
    "id": "1f707196-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Protons: +1, neutrons: 0, electrons: -1"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "What is cracking?",
    "id": "3991ab94-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The process of breaking down a long hydrocarbon into smaller hydrocarbons"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "What is the name given to the structure of diamond, graphite and silicon dioxide?",
    "id": "285ccd86-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Giant covalent"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "State a symptom of rose black spot.",
    "id": "2ca2eaba-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Damages leaves"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Some small plants in woodlands grow only in winter and dies before spring comes. Suggest why this occurs.",
    "id": "3bfe639a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "To avoid competiton for sunlight when large trees grow leaves and block out sunlight in spring/summer"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "If a cell is in a hypotonic solution, water will ___ (enter/leave) the cell.",
    "id": "1edf2dc6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Enter"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "What are abiotic factors? State two examples.",
    "id": "3bc8d4fa-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Non-living factors in an environment (eg. light intensity, soil pH, wind, humidity, temperature)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "How can metals be placed in order of their reactivity?",
    "id": "306976dc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Add the metals to water or acid and see which ones react the most (by how much fizzing there is)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "What is meant by the ionising power of radiation?",
    "id": "366dcb50-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "how likely it is to ionise atoms which it comes into contact with"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Where does differentiation occur in plants?",
    "id": "1f3de014-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Meristem/Root tip/Shoot tip"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "What chemical symbol represents a reversible reaction?",
    "id": "34e07530-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "_"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "Which gases were present in Earth's early atmosphere?",
    "id": "3ec54724-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Carbon dioxide water vapour and nitrogen with small amounts of methane and ammonia"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Reorder the following in increasing size order: Organ, cell, tissue, organ system, organism",
    "id": "229f6872-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Cell < Tissue < Organ < Organ system < Organism"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "What causes global dimming?",
    "id": "3e21a2a4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Particulates"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "Substances found in the periodic table are…?",
    "id": "350419d6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "elements"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Catcus' long roots is a feature to help compete for...?",
    "id": "3c0603ca-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Water"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "What charge will an ion of lithium take?",
    "id": "2805dc92-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "1+ (one electron in the outer shell, needs to lose it)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "State a similarity between plant cells and bacterial cells.",
    "id": "1e8b931e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Both have cell walls (but different material)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "Define atomic number",
    "id": "3529d554-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The number of protons in an atom (number of electrons is the same in a neutral atom)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What are some disadvantages of hydroelectricty?",
    "id": "22757832-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "blocks rivers preventing fish migration, unreliable (may not produce electricity during droughts)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "The _________ wire is a safety feature of appliances",
    "id": "2dd5535a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "earth"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "State a long-term effect of gonorrhoea.",
    "id": "2c93f62c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Long-term pelvic pain, infertility, ectopic pregnancies"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "What are decomposers?",
    "id": "3cd22f9a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Microorganisms that break down waste products and dead bodies"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State the function of the large intestine.",
    "id": "22ae608e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Absorb water from digested food"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Which two hormones are issued as fertility drug in IVF treatments?",
    "id": "348bf1cc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "FSH and LH"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "State one benefit of embryo screening.",
    "id": "37e30ad6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Know if child will have disorder/Able to decide if proceed with pregnancy or abortion"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "What is produced from the complete combustion of a hydrocarbon fuel?",
    "id": "3ef76ace-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "carbon dioxide and water"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Sodium fluoride is soluble. Explain what the easiest way for it to conduct electricity is",
    "id": "28532a42-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Dissolve it in water because this does not require high temperatures"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What is the equation linking energy transferred, power and time?",
    "id": "21fba264-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "P=E/t"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "What are periods in the periodic table?",
    "id": "1f9c6c6a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The rows in the periodic table"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What is a thermal insulator?",
    "id": "2290bc96-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A non-conductive material which reduces thermal energy transfers."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "What does 'plasmolysed' mean?",
    "id": "1eefb7fe-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The cell membrane becomes detached from cell wall"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "Explain why bromine is less reactive than chlorine (3 marks)",
    "id": "21e732de-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "More shells/electrons, more shielding (or weaker attraction from nucleus), harder to gain electrons"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "What are chromosomes?",
    "id": "1f153268-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Structures in the nucleus that carry genes"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "What is the unit of speed or velocity?",
    "id": "29e7cf20-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "metres per secons (m/s)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "Define 'aerobic respiration'.",
    "id": "2e4f473c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Exothermic reaction that breaks down glucose to release energy using oxygen"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "What is a displacement reaction?",
    "id": "21daf5e6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A reaction in which a more reactive element takes the place of a less reactive element in a compound"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State the function of the gall bladder.",
    "id": "22b369c6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Store bile before release into small intestine"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Define 'active transport'.",
    "id": "1ef6f26c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Movement of particles against the concentration gradient (low to high) using energy in the form of ATP"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "Reaction time is…",
    "id": "2a00b706-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "the time it takes a driver to react"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Explain why most giant covalent substances do not conduct electricity (3 marks)",
    "id": "28642630-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "There are no electrons/ions/charged particles that are free to move"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "What will absorb (stop) beta radiation?",
    "id": "36623380-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "about 5 mm aluminium"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "The overall charge on an atom is…",
    "id": "34ff4136-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "zero/neutral"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Give one charactersitc of a peacock that makes it a good competitor, and state what  it is competing for using this trait.",
    "id": "3bf1ec32-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Behaviour (eg. mating dance)/Attractive, colourful feathers to attract mate"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "Name the change of state when a liquid becomes a gas",
    "id": "31b089f4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "evaporation"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "What charge will an ion of beryllium take?",
    "id": "28084fd6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "2+ (two electrons in the outer shell, needs to lose them both)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "Which three elements are magnetic?",
    "id": "409197ce-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "iron, cobalt and nickel"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C8 Chemical Analysis",
    "question": "In chromatography, why must the substances be placed on a pencil line?",
    "id": "3ac162ac-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Pencil will not dissolve in the solvent"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Describe the I-V characteristic for a fixed resistor",
    "id": "2e0dcb68-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Current and potential difference are directly proportional, resistance is constant"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What is a kinetic energy store",
    "id": "2229dbc0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Energy stored in objects which move"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Will NaCl (l) conduct electricity?",
    "id": "283f7aba-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Yes"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "What are antigens?",
    "id": "2cbeba42-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Proteins on cell surface for cell recognition"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "What is the mass number of an atom?",
    "id": "1f7c7c7a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The number of protons + the number of neutrons in an atom"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "State the equation which links current, force, length of conductor and magnetic flux density",
    "id": "40ccab2a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "F=BIl"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "The reaction below is at equilibrium. What will occur when the pressure is increased? 2H~2~ ~(g)~ + O~2~ ~(g)~ = 2H~2~O ~(g)~",
    "id": "34f5e15e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The forward reaction will increase as there are fewer molecules on the right. This will reduce the total number of molecules and therefore the pressure."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Balance this ionic equation: Ca + Na^+^ = Ca^2+^ + Na",
    "id": "30f08500-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Ca + 2Na~+~ = Ca~2+~ + 2Na"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What is the equation for calculating efficiency from power?",
    "id": "220ad14e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Efficiency = useful power output/useful power input"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "How many electrons can go in the second and third shells?",
    "id": "1f951ca8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "8"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "How many domains and kingdoms do scientists now consider in classification?",
    "id": "394e2676-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "3 domains; 6 kingdoms"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Give one example of the use of genetically engineered bacterial cells.",
    "id": "38040484-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "To produce useful substances such as human insulin to treat diabetes."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "Define inert",
    "id": "21b941ee-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Unreactive"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "On a velocity time graph, when the line falls below the x-axis it indicates that the object is …",
    "id": "2a33709c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "moving backwards"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "State the relationship between size and surface area to volume ratio.",
    "id": "1f05d0de-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The bigger the size, the smaller the SA:V"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "What will happen to an animal cell if it is in a hypotonic solution?",
    "id": "1ee40cf6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Water enters cell --> burst"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Define 'embryonic stem cells'.",
    "id": "1f4adb3e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Stem cells from an early embryo that can differentiate into all cell types"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "What is a fuel?",
    "id": "3983d906-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A substance which when reacted with oxygen releases energy"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Explain in terms of electrons what occurs when beryllium bonds with oxygen (3 marks)",
    "id": "2823d936-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Two electrons transferred from beryllium to oxygen"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "How is the stomach adapted to protect itself from the hydrochloric acid?",
    "id": "252d2b38-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Thick mucus layer/quick renewal of epithelial layer"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Why do enzymes not work well at lower temperatures?",
    "id": "24f6b03a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Inactive (not enough KE to collide and bind to active site)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "What did the gold foil experiment prove?",
    "id": "1f77dd32-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "That atoms have dense nucleuses with a positive charge"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "Particles are arranged randomly, but touching in a …?",
    "id": "31f736a6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "liquid"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Briefly describe the second stage (mitosis) in the cell cycle.",
    "id": "1f2c35b2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Nucleus divides - One set of chromosomes is pulled to each end of the dividing cell"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What is the equation linking gravitationa field strength, gravitational potential energy and height?",
    "id": "21f6b380-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "E~p~=mgh"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "If balanced forces act on a stationary object it will …",
    "id": "2a49e444-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "remain stationary"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "What type of substance are methane and water?",
    "id": "287367ee-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Simple molecular (or simple molecules)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Define 'metabolism'.",
    "id": "24ed4edc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Sum of all reactions in a cell/body"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Why must patients finish their course of antibiotics every time?",
    "id": "38352d2a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "To ensure all bacteria are killed by the antibiotic, so none can survive to mutate and develop resistantce"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What is the equation for calculating efficiency from energy?",
    "id": "2208444c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Efficiency = useful energy output/total energy input"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Draw the circuit symbol for a variable resistor",
    "id": "2d1d7bcc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Describe the structure of simple covalent molecules",
    "id": "28786faa-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Strong covalent bonds between atoms, weak forces holding the molecules together"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "What is an important property of a solenoid/electromagnet as a magnet",
    "id": "40a415a2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "can be switched on and off with electric current"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name the hormone that decreases blood glucose level.",
    "id": "34307ba8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Insulin"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What is the reagent used to test for proteins?",
    "id": "24d2c8aa-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Biuret solution"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State a difference in the blood flowing in arteries and veins.",
    "id": "2559afa0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A: oxygenated, more nutrients, less wastes; V: deoxygenated, less nutrients, more wastes"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What is a gravitational potential store?",
    "id": "2236f080-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "energy storred in objects raised up against the force of gravity."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the pigment found in red blood cells that binds to oxygen.",
    "id": "2540d05c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Haemoglobin"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name a risk factor of developing cancer.",
    "id": "27d6f94a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Smoking, obesity, common viruses, UV exposure, genetic factors"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "Why are X-rays good for taking images of bone?",
    "id": "3bb71e90-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "absorbed by bone but transmitted through soft tissue"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "Moving objects with mass are said to have __________?",
    "id": "29bd9d86-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "momentum"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "How does carbon from fossil fuels get into the air?",
    "id": "3cf261ca-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Combustion"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Give a reason for deforestation.",
    "id": "3e3beb82-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Provide resources / Provide land for agriculture / Provide land to make biofuel"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "What is type 2 diabetes?",
    "id": "34413812-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Condition where body cells stop responding to insulin properly"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Explain why ionic compounds conduct electricity in solution",
    "id": "2846f20e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Because the ions are free to move"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What does classification of organisms mean?",
    "id": "383c1ebe-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Organisation of living things into groups based on their similarities"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "What is an atom?",
    "id": "1f5ebfaa-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The smallest part of an element that can still be recognised as that element"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "State the 7 heirarchical levels of the Linnaean classification system.",
    "id": "39402184-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Kingdom, phylum, class, order, family, genus, species"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "What problem is solved by recycling?",
    "id": "3ea6e856-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Avoiding landfills becoming full, which leads to pollution"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "Which products could be produced from the imcomplete combustion of a hydrocarbon fuel",
    "id": "3ef9daa2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "carbon dioxide, water, carbon monoxide, carbon particulates"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "metal oxide + acid = ?",
    "id": "30ae20f2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "salt + water"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What is the equation linking power, time and work done?",
    "id": "22034af0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "P=W/t"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C5 Energy Changes",
    "question": "How do we work out the overall energy change of a reaction?",
    "id": "31a3d6dc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Work out the difference between the energy needed to break all the bonds in the reactants and the energy released to form all the bonds in the products."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C3 Quantitative Chemistry",
    "question": "Which formula relates concentration, mass and volume?",
    "id": "2d0685de-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "concentration = mass/volume"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "How might an antibiotic be useless against a bacteria?",
    "id": "2cd2ac3c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Antibiotic resistance"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What does the term “recessive” mean?",
    "id": "36bc011c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The individual needs two copies of this allele for its phenotype to be seen."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "Explain why potassium is more reactive than lithium (3 marks)",
    "id": "21e4b13a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "More shells/electrons, less shielding (or weaker attraction from nucleus), easier to lose electrons"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "Draw a particle diagram for a gas",
    "id": "31eb68bc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "How does the trachea defend the body against pathogens?",
    "id": "2cb4c7e4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Secrete mucus to trap pathogens + Cilia move mucus up the trachea to be removed"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Why must we not use the coarse focus knob during high power magnification?",
    "id": "1e53562a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "It moves the stage by too much, may break the lens and the slide"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the reagent used to test for sugars.",
    "id": "24cdf8ac-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Benedict's solution"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What are some advantages of hydroelectricity?",
    "id": "22730bb0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "No carbon dioxide produced"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "What is global dimming?",
    "id": "3e1ea752-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Particulates made from combustion covers the atmosphere, reflecting sunlight so less light reaches the surface"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "What is the EM radiation with the longest wavelength?",
    "id": "3b0ab876-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Radio"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "How does the endocrine system bring about a change in our internal environment?",
    "id": "3423ef3c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Glands release hormones into bloodstream, which then travel to the target organ to produce an effect"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "What is the name given to the total amount of carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases emitted over the full lifecycle of a product, service or event",
    "id": "3ef51b0c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Carbon footprint"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "The greater the speed of a vehicle, the _________ the force required to stop the vehicle",
    "id": "2a0d4b7e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "greater"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "State an effect of insulin.",
    "id": "3437be9a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Increase glucose uptake by cells / more respiration / convert glucose to glycogen to store in liver and muscles / convert glucose to fat for storage"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Which organs produce lipases?",
    "id": "25173a6c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Pancreas and small intestine"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "What did Rutherford's experiment reveal?",
    "id": "363b844c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Atoms have a central area of positive charge with electrons surrounding it"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "What is the function of memory cells?",
    "id": "2cc62322-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Recognise same pathogen when it invades to produce large number of antibodies in short time"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "State changes are examples of ___________ change",
    "id": "31bb0302-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "physical"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Define 'tissue'.",
    "id": "229a94aa-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A group of cells with similar structure working together for a specific function"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "State an adaptation that polar bears have to survive in cold climates.",
    "id": "3c9ed906-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "More insulation (thick fat layer + fur)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "State an effect of glucagon.",
    "id": "343a1b36-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Convert glycogen to glucose/Make glucose from amino acids or fat"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Briefly describe how we can use stem cells to treat someone with type 1 diabetes.",
    "id": "1f5247ca-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Induce embryonic stem cells to produce healthy pancreas cells to make enough insulin"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What process is used to extract metals more reactive than carbon",
    "id": "3072daf6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Electrolysis"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "metal hydroxide + acid = ?",
    "id": "30abbe3e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "salt + water"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Give one charactersitic of a deer that makes it a good competitor.",
    "id": "3bef684a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Horns/Antlers"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C3 Quantitative Chemistry",
    "question": "What is Avogadro's number?",
    "id": "2cfcc422-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "6.022x10^23^"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "Explain why fluorine is more reactive than chlorine",
    "id": "21e23c98-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Fewer shells/electrons, less shielding (or stronger attraction from nucleus), easier to gain electrons"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "Particles move around randomly in a ….?",
    "id": "31f999c8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "gas"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "What is smog?",
    "id": "3e29c8ee-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Particulates + Acidic gases"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "How much mass a substance contains compared to it's volume is…",
    "id": "31a66d2a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "density"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C5 Energy Changes",
    "question": "If the reactants have less energy than the products, what kind of a reaction must have taken place?",
    "id": "319c2234-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "An endothermic one. The extra energy has been take in by the surroundings."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "What are antibodies?",
    "id": "2cbc52a2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Proteins that bind to specific antigens on pathogens"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "State one concern of screening embryos.",
    "id": "37e0ba60-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Causing miscarriage/Ethical concerns/Inaccurate results/Expensive"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "Name the change of state when a gas becomes a liquid",
    "id": "31b34e82-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "condensation"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "How does boiling point change with the length of an alkane?",
    "id": "3975de82-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The longer the alkane, the higher its boiling point"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name the hormone that affects the amount of urine produced by the kidney.",
    "id": "342ba98e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "ADH"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "How did the oceans reduce atmospheric levels of carbon dioxide in Earth's early atmosphere?",
    "id": "3ed206b2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Carbon dioxide dissolved in the oceans"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "How many pairs of chromosomes determine the sex of the individual?",
    "id": "37c9604a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "1"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Electric Current is….?",
    "id": "2dd9e172-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "the flow of electric charge"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "What is meant by a 'carbon sink'?",
    "id": "3e377732-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A place that stores carbon"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Suggest two ways to reduce air pollution.",
    "id": "3e32e460-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Use low-sulphur fuels / Set strict emission levels / Use biofuels / Use exhaust gas filters in power stations / Catalytic converters in cars"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What is a chromosome?",
    "id": "36b51316-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A thread-like structure which contains coiled up DNA and proteins."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What is the name for a method of reducing energy transfers by the use of non-conductive materials?",
    "id": "2293451a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "insulation"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "List three non-contact forces",
    "id": "29ac8d48-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "gravitational, electrostatic, magnetic"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name the three types of neurones that are involved in coordinating reflexes.",
    "id": "3417aa10-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Sensory, relay, motor neurones"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Define giant ionic lattice",
    "id": "28330c9e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A huge 3D network of ions"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "How do bacteria make you ill?",
    "id": "2c571f36-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Reproduce rapidly and damage cells + Produce toxins"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C8 Chemical Analysis",
    "question": "What is chromatography?",
    "id": "3ab56470-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A process to separate the constituents of a mixture"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "State the average length of the menstrual cycle.",
    "id": "34737228-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "28 days"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Explain in terms of electrons what occurs when lithium bonds with chlorine",
    "id": "2819d95e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "One electron transferred from lithium to chlorine"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Secondary consumers may be eaten by...?",
    "id": "3cc638b6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Tertiary consumers"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State the function of the stomach.",
    "id": "22a6edea-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Releases digestive enzymes to digest food"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Where does fertilisation occur in IVF treatment?",
    "id": "348e4544-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "In a Petri dish"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "State Newton's Second Law",
    "id": "2a4c5cec-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Force = mass x acceleration (The acceleration of an object is proportional to the resultant force acting on the object, and inversley proportional to the mass of the object)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What aspects of knowledge would be considered when suggesting evolutionary relationships?",
    "id": "395e966e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Similarties and differences in physical structures, genetics and biochemistry"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Why is the muscle wall of the left ventricle thicker than the right ventricle?",
    "id": "257a6c04-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "To generate more pressure to force blood all over the body (left side only to lungs)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "Electrical working is…?",
    "id": "22124fe6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "energy transferred when a charge moves through a potential difference"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State the two functions of bile.",
    "id": "252f9954-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Emulsifies fats + Neutralises food from stomach (HCl)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Define 'catalyst'.",
    "id": "24df2366-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A substance that speeds up chemical reactions but don't get used up"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "State a key difference between prokaryotes and eukaryotes.",
    "id": "1e74f8e8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Prokaryotes do not have a nucleus. Eukaryotes do."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "How many percent of your chromosomes have you inherited from your father?",
    "id": "1f1d6294-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "50%"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Give two examples of good carbon sinks.",
    "id": "3e39aed0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Forests + Peat bogs"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "What is a series circuit?",
    "id": "2de5a1a6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A circuit with only one route for charge to flow"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "What are the products of cracking?",
    "id": "39940d9e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Short alkanes and alkenes"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Define an ore",
    "id": "3075575e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A material containing enough metal in it for it to be economically worthwhile to extract the metal."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "The process of radiation removing electrons from atoms to form ions is called…?",
    "id": "35205cae-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "ionisation"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "A compressed spring is a store of ___________ energy",
    "id": "223e5852-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "elastic potential"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Name two conditions that particulates can cause.",
    "id": "3e2447f2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Global dimming + Smog"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Which part of the plant allows gases to diffuse in and out of leaves?",
    "id": "27a9f774-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Stomata"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "What is the frequency of the alternating current in UK mains electricity?",
    "id": "2e231572-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "50Hz"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "What are the effects of the oxides of nitrogen?",
    "id": "40037dfe-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "causes respiratory problems and acid rain"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "Give a use of visible radiation",
    "id": "3baa0a66-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Fibre optic communications"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "Write the equation linking frequency, wavelength and wave speed",
    "id": "3afcf402-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "v = fλ"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "What is the charge of each subatomic particle?",
    "id": "3649cc64-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "proton +1, neutron 0, electron -1"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Define 'extinction'.",
    "id": "3820724a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Permanent loss of all members of a species"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C10 Using resources",
    "question": "What is desalination?",
    "id": "401b2e5e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Removal of saly from sea water"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "State an effect on your body after anaerobic respiration.",
    "id": "2e656742-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Muscle fatigue"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "Name the three types of radiation",
    "id": "364e5e46-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "alpha, beta and gamma"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Name the person who developed the classification system.",
    "id": "393dc5ba-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Carl Linnaeus"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "Name the change of state when a solid becomes a gas (without passing through liquid form)",
    "id": "31b60ba4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "sublimation"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "What is graphene?",
    "id": "286e6280-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "One layer of graphite"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Suggest a chain of events initated by an asteroid collision that could lead to the extinction of dinosaurs.",
    "id": "3827515a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Asteroid impact causes huge fires and earthquakes --> volcanic eruptions --> dust/ash cloud covers atmosphere --> less sunlight reaches the Earth surface --> temp drop massively + plants die --> loss of food source led to other animals' extinction"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Explain the importance of active transport in plants.",
    "id": "1ef964e8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Root hair cells carry out AT to absorb mineral ions effectively in dilute soil"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "State the equation which links distance, force and work done",
    "id": "29c505d0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "W=Fs"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "What is the unit of the spring constant?",
    "id": "29e2a702-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Newtons per meter (N/m)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "What biological consequences does melting of ice caps bring about?",
    "id": "3e591176-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Loss of habitat --> some animals die --> reduce biodiversity"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "What are intermolecular forces?",
    "id": "287adc5e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Weak forces between molecules which hold them together"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "State one method to prevent the spread of disease.",
    "id": "2c5e8a96-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Isolation; Maintain good hygiene; Destroy vectors; Vaccination"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "What does it mean by 'net movement'?",
    "id": "1eb9dce2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Overall movement: particles can move in any direction, but generally speaking, most of the particles are moving in one particular direction, hence 'net' movement"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "Two like poles always ______",
    "id": "4052d962-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "repel"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "What is glycogen?",
    "id": "343c5f90-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Complex/Storage carbohydrate made up of glucose in liver and muscles"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Why is it important for the lungs to have a rich blood supply?",
    "id": "259d133a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Maintain steep concentration gradient for efficient diffusion"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "What is bioaccumulation?",
    "id": "3e0cd16c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Accumulation of chemicals in an organism"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "State the effect of increasing the concentration on the rate of reaction",
    "id": "34c82700-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Increases"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "Give one use of gamma rays",
    "id": "3bb4a5f2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Medical treatments"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the enzyme that digests starch.",
    "id": "2500949c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Amylase"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "How is a gamete different from a normal body cell?",
    "id": "3680a5a4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Half genetic information"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Define 'carcinogens'.",
    "id": "27c5d32c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Cancer-causing substances"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Is this process oxidation or reduction? F~2~ + 2e^-^ = 2F^-^",
    "id": "30eb527e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Reduction"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "What is the unit of mass?",
    "id": "29d681b6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "kilograms (kg)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What is the reagent used to test for lipids?",
    "id": "24d7b694-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Ethanol (+water)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "Why is the number of electrons in an atom equal to the number of protons?",
    "id": "1f7ef23e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "As their charges cancel out"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name the organ the produces hormones to control blood glucose level.",
    "id": "34351302-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Pancreas"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "What do plants make in anaerobic respiration?",
    "id": "305df352-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Ethanol and carbon dioxide"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Draw the circuit symbol for a voltmeter",
    "id": "2d27bd44-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Name the structure within which DNA is contained.",
    "id": "36a9696c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Chromosomes."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "How does being biconcave help red blood cells with their function?",
    "id": "2548a5c0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Increase SA:V for efficient diffusion"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "How can tobacco mosaic virus be spread?",
    "id": "2c74c838-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Direct contact/Vectors"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "What is a permanent magnet?",
    "id": "4079a9f2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A magnet that produces its own magnetic field."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Bile is an enzyme. True or false?",
    "id": "2534b6dc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "FALSE"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "On a distance time graph a curved line becoming horizontal represents…",
    "id": "2a21a4a2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "decelleration"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "The time needed for one wave to pass a given point is the…",
    "id": "3ae169c6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "period"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "Which plant did the heart drug digitalis originated from?",
    "id": "2cd51dc8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Foxgloves"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "What are producers?",
    "id": "3cbcdba4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Organisms that can make food/biomass from raw materials such as CO~2~ and water (eg. plants, algae)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "How does active transport differ from diffusion and osmosis?",
    "id": "1f00dd9a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "AT uses energy, D and O do not"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "State a symptom of malaria.",
    "id": "2cad304c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Fevers, shaking"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "The number of waves passing a point each second is the…",
    "id": "3ad482d8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Frequency"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "Two opposite poles always _______",
    "id": "40551ea2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "attract"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C8 Chemical Analysis",
    "question": "In chemistry what is a \"pure\" substance?",
    "id": "39a98c28-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A substance made of a single element or compound"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "metal + acid = ?",
    "id": "30a8c38c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "salt + hydrogen gas"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "State the units of volume",
    "id": "31e1f82c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "m3"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "Calculating the area under a velocity time graph gives the …",
    "id": "2a38678c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "distance travelled"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "The blue wire in a plug is the ________",
    "id": "2dc9e9ac-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "neutral"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "The process taking place when a wave enters a different density medium and changes direction",
    "id": "3af03cda-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Refraction"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C5 Energy Changes",
    "question": "State two uses of exothermic reactions",
    "id": "318d1c4e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Self-heating cans, hand warmers"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Name the process where a sperm and an egg cell fuse together.",
    "id": "3690f6de-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Fertilisation"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Why do cacti have swollen stems?",
    "id": "3cb54272-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Store water"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "What is the activation energy?",
    "id": "34d48d38-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The amount of energy a particle needs before it will be able to react when it collides with another particle"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "How do we calculate % change in mass?",
    "id": "1ef47ea6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "(final mass - intial mass)/initial mass x 100"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Give a reason for peat destruction.",
    "id": "3e3e341e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Provide fuel/garden compost"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What is the formula of copper (I) oxide",
    "id": "30e2f368-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Cu_O"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "What are the units of activity?",
    "id": "3511ef34-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Becquerels (Bq)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "Fctors which affect breaking distance are …",
    "id": "2a080e5c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "weather conditions, conditions of breaks and tyres"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "Food is a store of __________ energy.",
    "id": "223189d8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "chemical"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "Write the word equation to represent photosynthesis",
    "id": "3eccf6a4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "carbon dioxide + water _ oxygen + glucose"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C10 Using resources",
    "question": "How is water sterilised?",
    "id": "401869bc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Using chlorine, ozone or ultraviolet light"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Define ' digestion'.",
    "id": "24fbacd4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Breakdown of large insoluble molecules into smaller soluble substances"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Any greenhouse effect is bad for the Earth. True or false? Explain.",
    "id": "3e4f5dfc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "FALSE (essential to keep earth warm, vital for life)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What is genetic engineering?",
    "id": "37ff759a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The process which involves modifying the genome of an organism by introducing a gene from another organism to give a desired characteristic."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Explain in terms of electrons what occurs when magnesium bonds with oxygen",
    "id": "28215774-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Two electrons transferred from magnesium to oxygen"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "State the effect of increasing the surface area on the rate of a reaction",
    "id": "34c39dca-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Increases the rate"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "What does a step down transformer do?",
    "id": "2e2cd562-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "reduces p.d. to 230 V"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "What is the structure of a sperm cell that contains digestive enzymes to break down the surface of an egg cell?",
    "id": "1e95ba42-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Acrosome"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "State the equation which links current, potential difference and power",
    "id": "2def1704-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "P=IV"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "What can the group tell you about the electrons in an atom?",
    "id": "1f99dd06-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "How many electrons in the outer shell. E.g. carbon is in group 4 so has 4 electrons in the outer shell"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "Define isotope",
    "id": "3508c2a6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "An atom of the same element with different numbers of neutrons"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "What human activities increase methane levels?",
    "id": "3eee176c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Farming animals and landfill"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "State one risk or concern people may have about using stem cells.",
    "id": "1f5c43c4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Unethical to use aborted embryos; difficult and expensive project; cancer concern; viral infection/transmission"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Suggest a natural source of methane.",
    "id": "3e4a9146-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Growing rice and cattle"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "What is the unit of magnetic flux density?",
    "id": "40ba711c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Tesla (T)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C8 Chemical Analysis",
    "question": "What is a formulation?",
    "id": "3ab060ec-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A complex mixture designed as a useful product"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Give 3 effects of acid rain.",
    "id": "3e1bce4c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Kills plants; Destroys roots in soil; Acidifies bodies of water, killing marine organisms; Affects neighbouring countries; Acid snow kills young plants"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "For a given liquid, predict the products at each electrode",
    "id": "3177559e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Pure metal at cathode, non-metal at anode"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What are the three different types of fossils that can be formed?",
    "id": "38197684-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Mineralised skeleton; Undecayed due to trapped in ice or amber; Preserved traces of organisms (eg. footprints, leaves)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "What is abundance?",
    "id": "1f8b15c8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The % of atoms in a universe with a particular mass"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name a risk factor for type 2 diabetes.",
    "id": "3445f12c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Lack of exercise/Sugary diet/Obesity"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Define 'differentiation'.",
    "id": "1f33b4a4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The process where a cell becomes specialised/adapted to perform specific functions"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "What charge will an ion of Selenium take?",
    "id": "28175030-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "2- (group 6, so has 6 electrons in the outer shell and needs to gain two)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "What are two major problems from the exponential increase in human population?",
    "id": "3cfc1d82-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "More natural resources are used up + Produce more wastes --> decrease biodiversity"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C8 Chemical Analysis",
    "question": "Describe the melting and boiling points of impure substances",
    "id": "39b073ee-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "They change state at a range of temperatures"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "What ia a non-contact force?",
    "id": "29a79086-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A force between objects which are separated by space."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "The internal energy store of an object can be changed by…?",
    "id": "2245fd64-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "heating or cooling"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name a risk factor for obesity.",
    "id": "27ec133e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Poor/unbalanced diet; lack of exercise; High cholesterol diet"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Which hormone inhibits the release of both FSH and LH?",
    "id": "348286be-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Progesterone"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "What is \"collision theory\"?",
    "id": "34bf1bb0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The theory that chemical reactions only occur when particles collide with sufficient energy"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "Define count rate",
    "id": "35147632-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Number of decays recorded each second by a Geiger-Muller tube"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Particles which can be 'charges' in electric circuits are…",
    "id": "2de364cc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "electrons or ions"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "Define 'oxygen debt'.",
    "id": "2e67c258-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Amount of oxygen needed to break down lactic acid"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Name the gametes in plants.",
    "id": "3687b920-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Egg + Pollen"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "How did algae and plants reduce levels of carbon dioxide in Earth's early atmosphere?",
    "id": "3ed4e918-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "By photosynthesising"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What is used in radiotherapy?",
    "id": "27de173e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Targeted doses of radiation"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "How is classification helpful?",
    "id": "3957a57a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Helps us to understand evolutionary and ecological relationships"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "How are alveoli adapted for efficient gaseous exchange?",
    "id": "1f0b278c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Large SA, thin membrane (short diffusion distance), rich blood supply (maintain steep conc gradient)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "On a velocity time graph an upwards straight line represents …",
    "id": "2a2957d8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "acceleration"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "The region in a longitudinal wave where particles are closest together is a …",
    "id": "3ae3f2e0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "compression"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "Name a viral disease in plants.",
    "id": "2c6d59c2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Tobacco mosaic virus"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Illustrate the reflex pathway in a flowchart, showing all the components involved.",
    "id": "341c5dbc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "(Stimulus -->) Receptor --> Sensory neurone --> Relay neurone --> Motor neurone --> Effector (--> Response)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Which ions are in H~2~SO~4~",
    "id": "30ce4d14-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "2 ions of H^+^ and one SO~4~^2-^"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name a method to unblock a coronary artery in the heart.",
    "id": "257f8702-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Stent"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "Which pathogen does antibiotics destroy?",
    "id": "2ccdbf9c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Bacteria"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "How are photosynthetic cells adapted for photosynthesis?",
    "id": "1eaa53d0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Lots of chloroplasts with chlorophyll to absorb light"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "How many electrons are in the outer shell of an Oxygen atom?",
    "id": "1faecec8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "6"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "How does beta decay alter the atomic number of the parent nucleus?",
    "id": "3676f61c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "increases by 1"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name the component in the nervous system that processes the stimuli information.",
    "id": "33f882b6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Coordination centre"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Define 'osmosis'.",
    "id": "1ecb4f04-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Net movement of water molecules down the water concentration gradient through a partially permeable membrane"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "The maximum displacement of a point on a wave away from its undisturbed position is the…",
    "id": "3acfff38-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Amplitude"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Name the process(es) where water escapes from the oceans and into the clouds.",
    "id": "3ce5e44a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Evaporation and condensation"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "Flemming's left hand rule shows the relative directions of what things?",
    "id": "40a6a830-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Force, magnetic field and current"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "State the rule for resistance in a parallel circuit",
    "id": "2dbe6988-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "adding more resistors in parallel decreases resistance"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name a risk factor for type 2 diabetes.",
    "id": "27ee8ea2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Obesity; Unbalance diet (high sugar diet); Lack of exercise"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "What is the atomic number of an atom?",
    "id": "1f7a1e94-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The number of protons in an atom"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "Why is crude oil a finite resource?",
    "id": "396808d4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Because it takes longer to form than the rate at which we are using it up"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Describe and explain how prey population changes as predator population increases.",
    "id": "3cc88f76-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Prey population decreases as more predator eats more prey"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "What is a difference between prokaryotic and eukaryotic DNA?",
    "id": "1e814c1a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Prokaryotic DNA is circular; Eukaryotic DNA is linear"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Suggest a possible challenge in reducing carbon dioxide emission.",
    "id": "3eb20984-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Lack of scientific research on better engines or methods to reduce emission"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C5 Energy Changes",
    "question": "State two uses of endothermic reactions",
    "id": "318fc282-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Some cooling sports injury packs"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "State the four types of pathogens.",
    "id": "2c54ae40-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Bacteria, viruses, protists, fungi"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "What is the function of a nerve cell?",
    "id": "1e9ab722-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Carry electrical impulses"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Why is aluminium oxide mixed with cryolite when extracting aluminium?",
    "id": "31674e42-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "To lower the melting point"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "How do you calculate the number of neutrons in an atom?",
    "id": "1f816924-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Mass number - atomic number"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "What will happen to a plant cell if it is in a hypertonic solution?",
    "id": "1ee8b706-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Water leaves cell --> plasmolysed"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Why is bioaccumulation bad?",
    "id": "3e11b4e8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Chemical conc increases each trophic levels --> may reach fatal levels when get to the top consumer"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "Define mass number",
    "id": "35274f0a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The total number of protons and neutrons in an atom"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "What is an alloy?",
    "id": "29896624-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A mixture of two or more elements, at least one of which is a metal"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "Identify the element that has 3 shells of electrons and 7 electrons on its outer shell",
    "id": "1fb1ab34-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Chlorine"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "What is the unit for potential difference?",
    "id": "2dfe0660-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Volts (V)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Draw the circuit symbol for an LED",
    "id": "2d200982-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Which tumour leads to cancer - benign or malignant?",
    "id": "27d48232-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Malignant"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C10 Using resources",
    "question": "What do humans use resources for?",
    "id": "40086b84-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Warmth, shelter and food"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "What is more reactive, lithium or sodium?",
    "id": "21b44342-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Sodium"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Draw the circuit symbol for a thermistor",
    "id": "2d2cd6d0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Why do plants in dry and hot conditions have curled leaves?",
    "id": "3cade31a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Traps moist air --> reduce water vapour conc gradient --> Reduce transpiration"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What are some advantages of fossil fuels as an energy resource?",
    "id": "2259e860-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "reliable, cheap"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "Latent heat of vaporisation is for changing….?",
    "id": "31d7ec10-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "liquid to vapour (gas)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "How are evolutionary trees made?",
    "id": "395c40a8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "By looking at similarities and differences between different groups of organisms"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Why don't sulphur ions and oxygen ions form ionic bonds with each other?",
    "id": "282de2a0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Both have negative charges so would repel"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "What is the EM radiation with the shortest wavelength?",
    "id": "3b085068-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "gamma"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What is the positive test for lipids?",
    "id": "24da33ba-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "White milky layer"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "What is the definition of a magnetic field?",
    "id": "404e3e8e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The area around a magnet where a force acts on another magnet or magnetic material"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C10 Using resources",
    "question": "Give an example of a natural product that has been replaced by a synthetic product",
    "id": "4010a696-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Cotton has been replaced by polyester"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Apart from their humps, give one other adaptation of camels to help them reduce water loss.",
    "id": "3ca679ae-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Specially adapted kidneys /  Very little sweating"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Briefly describe the transpiration stream.",
    "id": "27b166d0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Constant movement of water through xylem from roots to leaves"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C10 Using resources",
    "question": "In the UK how is potable water produced?",
    "id": "4015f736-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Passing fresh water through filter beds and sterilising"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Briefly describe the first stage in the cell cycle.",
    "id": "1f29b274-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Cell size increase, DNA and organelle replication"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "State the rule for potential difference in a parallel circuit",
    "id": "2dbbeece-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "the potential difference across each branch in the circuit is the same"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Define 'benign tumours'.",
    "id": "27cf735a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Growth of abnormal cells contained in one area within a membrane, don't invade other tissues"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "State the equation of photosynthesis.",
    "id": "2e34301e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "6CO~2~ + 6H~2~O --> C~6~H~12~O~6~ + 6O~2~"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "State the genotype(s) that would result in cystic fibrosis.",
    "id": "37dc1a14-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "cc (homozygous recessive)."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What is the genotype of a male?",
    "id": "37cdef3e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "XY"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "What are the effects of particulates of fuels",
    "id": "4005f4e4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "cause global dimming and health problems for humans"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Resistance is…?",
    "id": "2de12072-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "caused by anything which opposes the flow of electric charge"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Name two ways in which water gets released from plants to the environment.",
    "id": "3cde6a94-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Transpiration + Respiration"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "Name a viral disease that leads to blindness and brain damage.",
    "id": "2c60f33a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Measles"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C10 Using resources",
    "question": "In what two ways can desalination be carried out?",
    "id": "401dd9c4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Reverse osmosis or distillation"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C5 Energy Changes",
    "question": "State the law of conservation of energy.",
    "id": "3179fd26-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Energy cannot be created or destroyed, it can only transferred from one place to another."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "The speed of an object in a particular derection is its ___________",
    "id": "2a124c00-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "velocity"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "What is the function of the slime capsule?",
    "id": "1e8dfabe-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Protect the cell"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "What is a compound?",
    "id": "1f640140-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A substance made of two or more different atoms chemically bonded together"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "Define 'health'.",
    "id": "2a589e1c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "State of physical and mental well-being"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "What is internal energy?",
    "id": "31c4f4f2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The total kinetic energy and potential energy of all the particles in a system"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Any substance can fit into the active site of an enzyme. True or false?",
    "id": "24e8c326-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "FALSE"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C5 Energy Changes",
    "question": "Give two examples of endothermic reactions.",
    "id": "318842b4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Thermal decomposition reactions, citric acid and sodium hydrogencarbonate."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C10 Using resources",
    "question": "What is the main disadvantage of desalination?",
    "id": "4020e42a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "It requires a large amount of energy"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What are the three domains?",
    "id": "3952f49e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Archaea, bacteria, eukaryota"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "What is an isotonic solution?",
    "id": "1ed55166-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A solution with the same solute conc as the cell"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Define 'mitosis'.",
    "id": "1f224746-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Cell division that produces two genetically identical daughter cells"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State a reason for setting the amylase solution, starch solution and the buffer in the water bath before the experiment.",
    "id": "2525e918-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "To ensure all of the same temp, so that temp will not affect the results (fair test)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Explain why zinc can be extracted from zinc oxide with carbon but magnesium cannot be extracted from magnesium oxide with carbon",
    "id": "306e1df4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Magnesium is more reactive than carbon (1), Zinc is less reactive than carbon (1), Carbon can therefore remove oxygen from zinc oxide but not magnesium oxide (1)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Explain how global dimming affect plant growth.",
    "id": "3e2721ac-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Cooling temperatures + Less sunlight --> Plants die due to insufficient photosynthesis"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "How does human sewage contribute towards land pollution?",
    "id": "3e00fb9e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Harmful microbes and bad chemicals lead to spread of diseases on land"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What is the function of heart valves?",
    "id": "257d0b8a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Prevent backflow of blood"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "What is an electromagnet?",
    "id": "40a0756e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A solenoid containing an iron core which increases its strength"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "Why can't antibiotics kill viruses?",
    "id": "2cd0417c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Viruses reproduce inside cells, antibiotics cannot enter cells without damaging the cell"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "State one organism that is prokaryotic.",
    "id": "1e775dfe-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Bacteria"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "State a symptom of gonorrhoea.",
    "id": "2c918090-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Yellow/green discharge from penis/vagina; pain on urination"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "Name the three subatomic particles",
    "id": "364508be-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "proton, neutron, electron"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "If a salt is in solution, how do you extract it as a solid?",
    "id": "30b55c0a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Allow the water to evaporate off and it will leave the salt behind as a solid."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "How many chromosomes are there in a human gamete?",
    "id": "3693555a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "23"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the process of the transport of dissoved sugars in plants.",
    "id": "27a4eb08-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Translocation"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Describe the I-V characteristic of a filament lamp",
    "id": "2e10244e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Resistance is not constant, it increases as p.d. increases"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "Define element",
    "id": "3501c294-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Contains only one type of atom"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "Name a use of radio waves",
    "id": "3b1c5716-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "TV and radio transmission"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "Defne half life",
    "id": "3516c0d6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The time taken for number of radioactive nuclei in a sample to halve OR time taken for count rate (or activity) from a sample to fall to half its initial value"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "What experiment did Rutherford do?",
    "id": "3539ed2c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Alpha particle scattering"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C8 Chemical Analysis",
    "question": "How can carbon dioxide be tested for?",
    "id": "3acac4c8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Bubble through limewater, turns it milky (cloudy)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "What are the effects of sulfur dioxide?",
    "id": "4000e8aa-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "causes respiratory problems and acid rain"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Which of the substances below has been oxidized and which has been reduced? 2Al + 2Fe^2+^ = 2Fe + 2Al^2+^",
    "id": "307f377e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Aluminium has been reduced and iron has been oxidised"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "What are isotopes?",
    "id": "1f88a1d0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Atoms of the same element with a different number of neutrons"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C3 Quantitative Chemistry",
    "question": "When an acid reacts with a metal, why does the mass decrease?",
    "id": "2cee15e4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Because a gas is produced and escapes"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Suggest why seed dispersal is considered an adaptation to avoid competition.",
    "id": "3c03727c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Seed is carried far away instead of landing right next to parent plant, so offspring plant doesn't compete with parent plant"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "The distance a vehicle travels while the driver is reacting is the …",
    "id": "29fbc732-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "thinking distance"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "How can the spread of gonorrhoea be stopped?",
    "id": "2c969ddc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Use condom; Limit sexual partners"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "State the function of the permanent vacuole.",
    "id": "1e6b0d24-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Contains cell sap to keep plant cells rigid, provide support"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Define 'active site'.",
    "id": "24e67c06-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The site on an enzyme where the substrate binds"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "What are the steps involved in fractional distillation?",
    "id": "397f2802-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Crude oil is vaporised, different molecules rise up the fractionating column and cool down. Condense at different points on the column."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "The stopping distance of a vehicle is the sum of the �",
    "id": "29f94fe8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "thinking and breaking distances"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "How can a high fat diet lead to coronary heart disease?",
    "id": "27f15f4c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Fat deposit in coronary arteries"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Name a substance that diffuses out of our cells to be removed.",
    "id": "1ec61b7e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Carbon dioxide, urea"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "What is the effect of thyroxine?",
    "id": "3451c9a2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Controls metabolic rate"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "State an adaptation of the leaf for efficient photosynthesis.",
    "id": "2e3dc1ec-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Broad leaves/Thin/Have chlorophyll/Air spaces/Guard cells to regulate stomata opening"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "What did Chadwick discover?",
    "id": "1f83ce58-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The neutron"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "What is a hydrocarbon?",
    "id": "396a4ef0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A compound made of atoms of carbon and hydrogen only"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name the hormone that stimulates the build-up of the uterus lining.",
    "id": "346a3f3c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Oestrogen"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "Which pathogen causes rose black spot?",
    "id": "2ca0767c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Fungi"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What is a dilute acid?",
    "id": "30c26774-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "An acid where there are fewer acid particles in the water."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What is the reactivity series?",
    "id": "3067166c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A list of elements ordered by their reactivity"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "What is an alpha particle?",
    "id": "3650a91c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "two protons and two neutrons"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "The right hand thumb rule shows relative direction of…",
    "id": "40c630c4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "current and magnetic field around a wire"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What is a base?",
    "id": "30952da4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A metal oxide, hydroxide or carbonate that will react with an acid. E.g. copper oxide"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Which organ system transports substances to and from body cells?",
    "id": "2543b68c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Circulatory system"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "State four sources of water pollution.",
    "id": "3e05c64c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Untreated sewage + Fertilisers + Industrial wastes + Pesticides and herbicides"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "A change which creates new products and cannot be reversed is _________ change",
    "id": "31bfcf7c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "chemical"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "What is the unit of the spring extension?",
    "id": "29e5614a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Metres (m)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Where does lipid digestion occur?",
    "id": "251e8722-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Small intestine"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C8 Chemical Analysis",
    "question": "How can chlorine be tested for?",
    "id": "3acd88e8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Bleaches damp litmus paper white"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "What is the greenhouse effect?",
    "id": "3e4ceaa4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Thermal energy from the sun reaches the earth and some are reflected. Greenhouse gases absorb these reflected thermal energy and keep Earth warm"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "What are primary consumers? Give an example.",
    "id": "3cc1a36e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Animals that eat producers + Any herbivores (eg. cows, sheep, rabbits)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What is a strong acid?",
    "id": "30b7c454-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "An acid which completely splits up into its ions in water. E.g. when HCl is in water all the HCl molecules split up into H_ and Cl_"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Describe the state of the diaphragm as we breathe in.",
    "id": "25934a80-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Contracts and flattens"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "What is the function of a scale bar?",
    "id": "1e56d43a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "To allow us to calculate the actual size of the sample using I=AM"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "What substance makes up plants' cell walls?",
    "id": "1e70072a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Cellulose"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What elements make up carbohydrates?",
    "id": "24b7a444-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "C, H, O"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the two ways to treat cancer.",
    "id": "27d96928-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Chemotherapy, radiotherapy"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Define acids in terms of ions",
    "id": "308655fe-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A substance which releases H_ ions in solution"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "What is a double-blind trial?",
    "id": "2ce69f80-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Neither the doctors nor the patients know who gets the real drug/placebo"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Current flows into an appliance through the _______ wire",
    "id": "2dd0c506-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "live"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C10 Using resources",
    "question": "How is phytomining carried out?",
    "id": "4034352a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Plants absorb metal compounds, are harvested and then burned to produce ash"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "What is the EM radiation with the lowest frequency?",
    "id": "3b0f601a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Radio"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "Draw an electron shell diagram of a Li atom",
    "id": "1fabb2e2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "2, 1"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C5 Energy Changes",
    "question": "What are reactants?",
    "id": "3192446c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The substances involved in a chemical reaction"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the blood vessel type that carries blood from the heart to other parts of the body.",
    "id": "254fe236-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Artery"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Which side of the heart has deoxygenated blood - right or left?",
    "id": "2573442e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Right"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "The distance from a point on one wave to the equivalent point on the next wave is the …",
    "id": "3ad23780-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "wavelength"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "Calcuating the gradient of a velocity time graph gives the …",
    "id": "2a35e49e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "acceleration"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "What EM wave is used for satellite communication?",
    "id": "3b1eac82-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "microwave"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "In this reaction, what has been oxidised and what has been reduced? 2Al + 3Ca^2+^ = 2Al^3+^ + 3Ca",
    "id": "30fb035e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Al has been oxidised, Ca^2+^ has been reduced"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Name the organ that produces sperm cells.",
    "id": "368c6790-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Testes"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What is used in chemotherapy?",
    "id": "27dbc9e8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Chemicals to kill cancer cells, but also healthy cells in the process"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "What are hormones?",
    "id": "34267a0e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Chemical signals used for controlling the body's functions, such as during homeostasis."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "The limit of proportionallity of a spring is?",
    "id": "29f45970-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "the length a spring can be stretched to before it no longer returns to its original length"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What are the units of work done?",
    "id": "2205c4a6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "joules"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "In the electrolysis of sodium chloride solution, what are the products?",
    "id": "316f2d56-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Chlorine gas and hydrogen gas"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "Give two examples of contact forces",
    "id": "29aa0e2e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "e.g. friction, air resistance"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "How does gamma radiation alter the mass and atomic number of the parent nucleus",
    "id": "36794016-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "unchanged (energy is released as the particles in the nucleus reorganise to a lower energy arrangement)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "A typical cycling speed is …",
    "id": "2a3faf24-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "6 m/s"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "What is the colour change when an alkene reacts with bromine water?",
    "id": "39a230f4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Turns from orange to colourless"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Why does the tissue sample need to be stained before looking at it under the microscope?",
    "id": "1e4907ba-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "To visualise/see structures clearly"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State the function of the small intestine.",
    "id": "22abecd2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Digest food and absorb nutrients from digested food"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "Both thinking and breaking distance are affected by which factor?",
    "id": "2a0ac7e6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "speed of vehicle"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Which organs produce amylase?",
    "id": "25123364-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Salivary glands and pancreas"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "As decomposers break down organic material, what is released into the soil? How does it return to organisms?",
    "id": "3cd99dac-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Mineral ions (eg. nitrates) --> taken into producers through roots to build biomass (eg. proteins)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Draw the circuit symbol for an LDR",
    "id": "2db07b0c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name the 'master gland' that secretes a variety of hormones.",
    "id": "34293f00-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Pituitary gland"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What can be used to replace a damaged heart valve?",
    "id": "25847866-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Biological or mechanical valves"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C10 Using resources",
    "question": "What is potable water?",
    "id": "4013699e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Water that is safe to drink"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What are some advantages of wind power?",
    "id": "226e06f6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "No carbon dioxide produced"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Describe and explain how predator population changes as prey population increases.",
    "id": "3ccfc188-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Predator population increases, as more food/prey available, more predator and eat to survive and reproduce"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "How does beta decay alter the mass number of the parent nucleus?",
    "id": "3674b00a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "stays the same"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "How does flammability change with the length of an alkane?",
    "id": "397a8630-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The longer the alkane, the less flammable it is"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What is a salt?",
    "id": "309cb59c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A compound formed when some or all of the hydrogen from an acid is replaced by a metal. E.g. CuSO_, copper sulphate, where copper has replaced H from H_SO_"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "Heating is…?",
    "id": "221ce51e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A pathway to transfer energy"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the condition that babies may have if their mothers drink lots of alcohol during pregnancy.",
    "id": "27fb5f06-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Fetal alcohol syndrome"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What are some disadvantages of nuclear fuel?",
    "id": "226425f0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "nuclear waste remains radioactive for thousands of years. Expensive to build and decommission"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Increasing the rate of photosynthesis will ________ (increase/decrease) the rate of transpiration.",
    "id": "27b3d960-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Increase"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "What makes up vaccines?",
    "id": "2cc13ae2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Dead/Inactive pathogens"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "Give one use of yeast doing anaerobic respiration.",
    "id": "3060343c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Making bread/alcohol"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Will NaCl(s) conduct electricity?",
    "id": "283a538c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "No"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Briefly describe the lock- and-key model.",
    "id": "24eaffce-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Substrate fits into the active site to form enzyme-substrate complex --> Reaction occurs --> Enzyme releases products and binds to another substrate"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Arctic foxes' fur coat changes from grey to white during winter. Suggest two reasons why.",
    "id": "3ca907b4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Reduce heat loss by radiation + Better camouflage in the snow"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What are some disadvantages of tidal energy?",
    "id": "227f1f54-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "unreliable - tides vary, may damage tidal ecosystem"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "Energy stored in particles because of their position is…?",
    "id": "31c9d7f6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "potential energy"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Why do some plants have thorns?",
    "id": "3cb053a2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Prevent predation by herbivores"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Explain why resistance increases with increased p.d. in a filament lamp",
    "id": "2e127e92-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "temperature increases causing ions to vibrate and increasing collisions with electrons flowing through the filament"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What does the term “heterozygous” mean?",
    "id": "36c0b374-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The individual has two different alleles for this gene."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "When a spring is stretched and its length is permanently altered it is known as ___________  ____________",
    "id": "29f1eabe-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Inelastic deformation or inelastic behaviour"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "Acceleration of falling objects close to the earth is ________",
    "id": "2a17775c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "9.8 m/s2"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Weeds' rapid growth in height is a feature to help compete for...?",
    "id": "3c0adfc6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Light"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What are some advantages of biofuels?",
    "id": "22692636-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "carbon neutral, reliable"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the tissue that covers and protects the surface of plants.",
    "id": "259f8d68-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Epidermal tissue"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Define 'gametes'.",
    "id": "3695a508-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Sex cells"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the large vessel that brings oxygenated blood out of the heart to the body.",
    "id": "25780306-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Aorta"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "State the genotype(s) that would result in polydactyly.",
    "id": "37d5501c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "PP or Pp (homozygous dominant or heterozygous for this gene)."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "What is the unit of frequency?",
    "id": "3aff380c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Hertz (Hz)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Which hormone stimulates the release of LH?",
    "id": "34803e7c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Oestrogen"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Give 4 reasons why the fossil record is incomplete.",
    "id": "381bdc4e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "1. Many earliest life forms are soft-bodied; 2. Most organsisms did not become fossilised; 3. Most early fossils were destroyed by geological activity; 4. Many fossils are not yet found"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "Absorption of radiation by an atom may result in ____________ moving to a ________________ energy level",
    "id": "352e5aa2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "electrons, higher"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "State the equation which links charge flow, energy transferred and potential difference",
    "id": "2df62a30-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "E=QV"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "The distance and object moves and the direction in which it moves is known as the _________",
    "id": "2a0fb9b8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "displacement"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Which hormone(s) are used as contraceptive pills?",
    "id": "3484d342-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Oestrogen and progesterone"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "How does light intensity affect rate of transpiration?",
    "id": "27be0bb0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "More light increases rate"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "Does an irradiatied object become radioactive itself?",
    "id": "351dd9a2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "no"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What term is used to describe a method for reducing unwanted energy transfers by reducing friction?",
    "id": "228e4830-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "lubrication"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "Particles are arranged regularly in a ….?",
    "id": "31f4d4b0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "solid"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Why are transformers used?",
    "id": "2e2f2baa-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "reduce current so that less heat is lost in cables, increases efficiency"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "What is the general formula for alkanes?",
    "id": "39739474-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "CnH2n+2 (the n and 2n are small)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "State one symptom of Salmonella poisoning.",
    "id": "2c85967c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Fever/Abdominal cramps/diarrhoea/vomiting"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "Why doesn't temperature increase during evaporation",
    "id": "31effa58-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Energy is being used to weaken forces between particles"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "Refraction changes both the _________ and ___________ of a wave",
    "id": "3af2b276-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "direction and speed"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Explain why graphite conducts electricity",
    "id": "28669af0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Has delocalised electrons between the layers that can move through the graphite"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C5 Energy Changes",
    "question": "What are products?",
    "id": "3194b27e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The substances formed when reactants have a chemical reaction"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "State the law of conservation of momentum",
    "id": "29c010de-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "In a closed system the total momentum before an event is equal to the total momentum after an event."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What are some disadvantages of geothermal energy?",
    "id": "227a4eca-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "fluids drawn from ground may contain greenhouse gases such as CO~2~ and methane.These contribute to global warming"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "By which cell division type does cloning occur?",
    "id": "1f42f5f4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Mitosis"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "Which pathogen causes gonorrhoea?",
    "id": "2c8ac412-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Bacteria"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Define 'community'.",
    "id": "3bc3e90e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A group of interdependent organisms that are made of different species"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "In terms of electrons, what do group 1 elements have in common?",
    "id": "1fb47a62-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "1 electron in the outer shell"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Why do some plants have long roots?",
    "id": "3cb2a7ba-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Increase water uptake"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Which two female hormones does the ovaries release during the menstrual cycle?",
    "id": "3478dc68-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Oestrogen and progesterone"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What are the six kingdoms?",
    "id": "39554c9e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Archaebacteria, eubacteria, protista, fungi, plants, animals"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Briefly describe how an artificial pacemaker works.",
    "id": "25893e1e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Sends strong, regular electrical signals to the heart to stimulate it to contract properly"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Briefly describe how tobacco smoke causes cardiovascular diseases.",
    "id": "27e74052-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Increase heart rate, damage artery lining, increase risk of clot formation, increase blood pressure"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the part of the plant that waterproofs the leaf surface.",
    "id": "25a2011a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Waxy cuticle"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "How does stomata help maintain efficient gas exchange in leaves?",
    "id": "1f102a3e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Allow gases to move in and out of leaf, maintaining steep concentration gradient"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Briefly describe the cell cycle.",
    "id": "1f1fd3f8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Cell content (including DNA) is replicated, mitosis occurs to make two genetically identical cells"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "What are reflex actions?",
    "id": "34156926-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Automatic and rapid actions that do not involve the conscious parts of the brain"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "Was the Plumb Pudding model correct?",
    "id": "3537a008-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "no"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State a risk of drinking alcohol during pregnancy.",
    "id": "27f8e1e0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Miscarriage/Stillbirths/Premature births/Low birthweight"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "What is Le Chatelier's principle?",
    "id": "34ee5a2e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "When a reaction at equilibrium is changed, it will seek to counteract that change"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Explain why ionic compounds do not conduct electricity when solid",
    "id": "284476be-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Because the ions are not free to move"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "What is a beta particle?",
    "id": "365311e8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "an electron"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "On a distance time graph a horizontal line represents…",
    "id": "2a24760a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "stationary"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Which ions are always present in a solution of an alkali?",
    "id": "309a06ee-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "OH_"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Into what is the gene inserted?",
    "id": "3808ab2e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A vector"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "How do the extensions in root hair cells help with their function?",
    "id": "1ea4ddce-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Increase surface area for efficient water absorption"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "What is the unit of charge flow?",
    "id": "2df8aba2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Coulomb ( C )"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name a source of ionising radiation.",
    "id": "2800f326-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "UV light from sun/Radioactive materials in soil, water, air/Medical and dental X-rays/Accidents in nuclear power stations"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Why is having a high biodiversity important to form stable ecosystems?",
    "id": "3cf9b772-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Each species becomes less dependent on specific species for food/shelter --> less pressure on certain species which could've lead to extinction --> all species populations are balanced"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "What is the difference between preclinical testing and clinical trials?",
    "id": "2ce185a4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "PT: Use cells, tissues, animals; CT: Use healthy volunteers and patients"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "Factors which influence reaction time are…",
    "id": "2a059e60-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "tiredness, drug, alcohol, distractions"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "A magnetic material which becomes a magnet when placed in a magnetic field is a _______ _________",
    "id": "40884700-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "induced magnet"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "When a spring is stretched and can then return to its original length it is known as __________ _______________",
    "id": "29ef6d66-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "elastic deformation or elastic behaviour"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What are some disadvantages of wind power?",
    "id": "22707198-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "unreliable, expensive to construct"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State the function of the liver in the digestive system.",
    "id": "22a9742a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Produces bile for lipid digestion"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "What has to happen to the cell before mitosis to ensure we can two genetically identical daughter cells?",
    "id": "1f3141a6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "DNA and organelles must replicate before division"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Why is important to protect and regenerate rare habitats?",
    "id": "3ea1f346-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "To allow specifically adapted species to live in nature again (as they cannot live in \"normal\" conditions)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "Define 'placebo'.",
    "id": "2ce40ab8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A medicine that does not contain the active drug being tested"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "State Newton's Third Law",
    "id": "2a4ebcbc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Whenever two objects interact, the forces they exert on each other are equal and opposite"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "On a velocity time graph a horizontal line along the x-axis represents…",
    "id": "2a30b0c8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "stationary object"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "By which cell division type does asexual reproduction rely on?",
    "id": "367bef6e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Mitosis"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "When a new cell is formed through fertilisation, how does it divide?",
    "id": "36a1e0fc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Mitosis."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "Which radiation is used in sun tanning?",
    "id": "3bac7ada-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "UV"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name the type of neurone that carries impulses to the central nervous system.",
    "id": "33ff8ba6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Sensory neurone"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "Radiating is…?",
    "id": "221a6dfc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The  transfer of energy by waves."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "How does a decrease in biodiversity have a negative impact on humans?",
    "id": "3e42f800-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Loss of potential new sources of food and medicine / Loss of resources"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "State three traits plants might be genetically engineered to have.",
    "id": "3801c390-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "1. Resistant to insect attack"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Draw the circuit symbol for a battery",
    "id": "2d16090a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "State the trend in the melting points of the alkali metals",
    "id": "21c0a4ac-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Gets lower down the group"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State the function of platelets.",
    "id": "254d6c36-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Blood clotting"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "What is interdependence?",
    "id": "3bd0b0f8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A relationship that describes how all species within a community depend on each other to survive"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "Define peer review",
    "id": "3525086c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Checking of scientific results by other scientific experts"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Potential difference between two points in a circuit is….?",
    "id": "2ddc2680-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "the work done when a couloumb of charge passes between the points."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C3 Quantitative Chemistry",
    "question": "If the volume of water in a solution is increased, what happens to its concentration?",
    "id": "2d0b84a8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Decreases"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "An inflated balloon is a store of __________ energy",
    "id": "2240daaa-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "elastic potential"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "Physical changes are ones which can be _____________",
    "id": "31bd55bc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "reversed"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "The binomial name of an organism is made up of two words. What does each word represent of that organism?",
    "id": "394707a6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The first word  is the genus; second word is the species"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Why do cacti have spine-like leaves?",
    "id": "3cb7dd98-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Reduce SA --> reduce water loss"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "On a distance time graph a straight line represents…",
    "id": "2a1c836e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "constant speed"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "How does temperature affect enzymes' rate of reaction?",
    "id": "24f1cffc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "As temp increases, RoR increases until after optimum"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What is a phenotype?",
    "id": "37c48f02-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The displayed characteristic due to the interactions between alleles (e.g. red flowers)."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "What is a finite resource?",
    "id": "396582a8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "One that will run out"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "Which pathogen causes malaria.",
    "id": "2ca569b6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Protists"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What is cystic fibrosis?",
    "id": "37d78fe4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A condition which causes sticky mucus to build up in the lungs."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "What's the range of beta radiation in air?",
    "id": "365d9186-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "medium - about 1 m"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "Which rule can be used to determine the direction a motor will rotate?",
    "id": "40cf8ff2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Flemming's left hand rule."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "What is a fullerene?",
    "id": "2870ec62-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Substance made of carbon atoms arranged in a cage"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C10 Using resources",
    "question": "What is a low grade ore?",
    "id": "40311c5a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Rock with only a small amount of metal compound in it"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "How can measles spread?",
    "id": "2c636098-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Droplet infection"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "What are secondary consumers? Give an example.",
    "id": "3cc3ef8e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Animals that eat primary consumers + Any carnivores (eg. lions, foxes, eagles)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "Why have theories about Earth's early atmosphere developed and changed over time?",
    "id": "3ec7dde0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Evidence is limited"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What are the units of gravitational field strength?",
    "id": "21f924a8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "newtons per kilogram"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What is the law of conservation of energy?",
    "id": "2295ac88-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Energy cannot be created and destroyed but only transferred from one store to another."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "What is unit of gravitational field strength?",
    "id": "29d8f18a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "newtons per kilogram (N/kg)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "If balanced forces act on a moving object it will …",
    "id": "2a477c68-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "continue to travel at a constant speed"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "State three factors that affect the rate of diffusion.",
    "id": "1ebc57ba-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Concentration gradient, temperature, surface area"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What causes variation within a population?",
    "id": "37ec3124-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Mutations."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "What is the rate of a chemical reaction in terms of products?",
    "id": "34b0f026-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "How quickly the products in a reaction are formed"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "Balance the below equation and explain why it is a displacement reaction: KBr + Cl~2~ = KCl + Br~2~",
    "id": "21dfb860-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "2KBr + Cl~2~ = 2KCl + Br~2~ , chlorine has displaced bromine as it is more reactive"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "Why did Mendeleev put some elements in groups?",
    "id": "1fa16a4e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Because they had similar properties (e.g. they reacted violently with water)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Define 'stem cell'.",
    "id": "1f36333c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Undifferentiated cell with the potential to become specialised"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "What is the range of gamma radiation in air?",
    "id": "365b37ba-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "unlimited in air"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "What are biotic factors? State two examples.",
    "id": "3bcb97b2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Living factors in an environment (eg. predators, competitors, pathogens/microorganisms)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What two structures change the pressure inside the chest cavity to ventilate lungs?",
    "id": "2590b298-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Intercostal muscles + Diaphragm"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Explain in terms of electrons what occurs when lithium bonds with fluorine",
    "id": "281eda9e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "One electron transferred from lithium to fluorine"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Describe and explain how prey population changes as predator population decreases.",
    "id": "3ccd5b00-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Prey population increases, as less predators hunting them, more prey can survive and reproduce"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "Is respiration endothermic or exothermic?",
    "id": "2e5411c2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Exothermic"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What is the name for a reaction where oxygen is removed from a compound?",
    "id": "306bbb54-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Reduction"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "A typical walking speed is …",
    "id": "2a3ad422-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "1.5 m/s"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "State the equation which links charge flow, current and time",
    "id": "2dea3036-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Q=It"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "At which electrode would Cl^-^(aq) turn into Cl~2~(g)?",
    "id": "31521fae-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Anode (needs to lose electrons)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What is antibiotic resistance?",
    "id": "3829a36a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Bacteria becoming resistant means it cannot be killed by a certain antibiotic"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Which ions always react together in a neutralization reactions between acids and alkalis?",
    "id": "30a4004a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "H^+^ and OH^-^"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "What is the speed of electromagnetic radiation?",
    "id": "3b060754-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "300 000 000 m/s"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Hydrochloric acid in the stomach breaks down food. True or false?",
    "id": "25373d80-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "FALSE - provides optimum pH for pepsin and kills bacteria, NOT digest food"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "What will happen to an animal cell if it is in a hypertonic solution?",
    "id": "1ee1a09c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Water leaves cell --> shrivelled"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Describe three adaptations of exchange surfaces.",
    "id": "1f08bdbc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Large SA, thin membrane/surface, ability to maintain high conc difference"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "Why is cracking important?",
    "id": "3996c2c8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Because smaller hydrocarbons are more useful than longer ones"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "What is herd immunity?",
    "id": "2cc8d8a6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Large proportion of population is immune to a disease"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What is a neutralisation reaction?",
    "id": "30a19e22-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A reaction involving an acid that results in a neutral solution"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "State the specific name given to extremophiles that are adapted to live in high temperatures.",
    "id": "3c11eb9a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Thermophiles"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Balance this ionic equation: Al + Ca^2+^ = Al^3+^ + Ca",
    "id": "30f5cd08-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "2Al + 3Ca^2+^ = 2Al^3+^ + 3Ca"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "Draw a transverse wave and label the wavelength and amplidtue",
    "id": "3af793f4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Chromosomes are arranged in ___ pairs in a human body cell.",
    "id": "1f1ad0c4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "23"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "There are small proportions of water vapour, noble gases and which other gas in Earth's current atmosphere?",
    "id": "3eb9e500-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "carbon dioxide"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Name the process where water is rained down from the clouds.",
    "id": "3ce36fbc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Precipitation"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the protease that works well in the stomach.",
    "id": "2508376a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Pepsin"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the vessel that brings deoxygenated blood from the heart to the lungs.",
    "id": "256e3b5a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Pulmonary artery"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "Name LiOH",
    "id": "21d2f918-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Lithium hydroxide"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Explain why diamond has a high melting point",
    "id": "2861c660-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Giant structure, Strong covalent bonds between the atoms, requires a lot of energy to break"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "State one factor to maintain in a greenhouse for optimal plant growth.",
    "id": "2e4cc804-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "High CO~2~ levels / Constant light / Appropriate temperatures / Regulate watering"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "What is the unit of wavelength?",
    "id": "3b0189cc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "metres (m)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State an observation to determine when the amylase has completed its digestion of starch.",
    "id": "252376ec-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Iodine remains brown-red rather than turning blue-black"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "Define 'pathogens'.",
    "id": "2a562146-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Microorganisms that cause diseases"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "Draw the magnetic field between two unlike poles.",
    "id": "40c37082-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "What are alkenes used for?",
    "id": "399d9d0a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "As a starting material to make more useful chemicals"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "A moving object is a store of ____________ energy",
    "id": "22347a3a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "kinetic"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C10 Using resources",
    "question": "How can copper be produced from the products of phytomining or bioleaching?",
    "id": "403ac96c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Electrlysis or displacement with scrap iron"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "What living materials are used in preclinical testing?",
    "id": "2cdf1c88-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Cells, tissues, live animals"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "Name the microorganism that produces penicillin.",
    "id": "2cda06f8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Penicillium"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What is the equation linking kinetic energy, mass and velocity?",
    "id": "21ec31bc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "E~k~= 0.5mv^2^"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "We cannot predict when a given atom will decay, this means that radioactive deacy is ….?",
    "id": "350d555a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "random"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Explain how household and industrial wastes pollute land.",
    "id": "3e036b5e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Take up space in landfills + Toxic/radioactive chemicals --> poison soils + destorys habtitats"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "In a circuit the potential difference causes …..?",
    "id": "2ddebc9c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "charge to flow"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "Where is the strongest field in an electromganet created by a coil of wire?",
    "id": "409b09f8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "inside the coil"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the cell that contains lots of chloroplasts for photosynthesis.",
    "id": "25a4781e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Palisade mesophyll cells"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "Sketch the heating curve for water",
    "id": "31e4426c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "Oscillations are at right angles to the direction of travel in a ____________ wave",
    "id": "3adeffba-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "transverse"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Do negative ions move to the anode or the cathode?",
    "id": "310d728c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Anode"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "Painkillers destroy the pathogens in our body. True or false?",
    "id": "2ccb41b8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "FALSE"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "What state is chlorine at room temperature?",
    "id": "21c5f83a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Gas"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What is the positive result for proteins?",
    "id": "24d54c38-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Biuret turns from blue to purple"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "Name the change of state when a solid becomes a liquid",
    "id": "31ae123c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "melting"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "How does carbon from animals get into the atmosphere?",
    "id": "3ced5928-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Respiration/Decay (or decomposition)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "A reaction is at equilibrium when some product is removed. What will occur?",
    "id": "34f34c3c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The forward reaction will increase as that will increase the amount of product"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Draw the circuit symbol for a lamp",
    "id": "2d229cba-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Potential difference between the neutral wires and others in the plug should be ____ V",
    "id": "2dd796d8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "0V"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Which hormone inhibits the release of FSH?",
    "id": "347df7b6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Oestrogen"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "Two reactants require 30kJ to turn into products. What energy transfer is involved when the products turn into reactants?",
    "id": "34e52cb0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "30kJ is released"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Balance the equation: O~2~ --> O^2-^ + e^-^",
    "id": "315a4aee-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "O~2~ = 2O^2-^ + 4e^-^"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "What are communicable diseases?",
    "id": "2a53acf4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Diseases caused by pathogens that can be transmitted from one individual to another"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "State the equation which links current, power and resistance",
    "id": "2df18610-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "P=I~2~R"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "What state is fluorine at room temperature?",
    "id": "21c34fd6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Gas"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Will NaCl (aq) conduct electricity?",
    "id": "283cbe42-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Yes (aq stands for aqueous which means it is dissolved in water)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "The single force which has the same effect as the combination of all the different forces acting on an object is the ______________   _______________.",
    "id": "29b8c77a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "resultant force"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Explain in terms of electrons what occurs when magnesium bonds with chlorine",
    "id": "2826486a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "One electron transferred from magnesium to two different chlorine atoms"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "Latent heat of fusion is for changing…?",
    "id": "31d59884-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "solid to liquid"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Why can substances diffuse easily between capillaries and the cells?",
    "id": "255ed50c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Thin capillary walls (one cell thick)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What is the relationship between the strength of an acid and its pH?",
    "id": "30bd36d2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "As an acid increases in strength the pH decreases."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "What will absorb (stop) alpha radiation?",
    "id": "365fe33c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "paper/skin"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "List the 4 energy transfer pathways.",
    "id": "2221e2ee-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Mechanical working, electrical working, radiating and heating"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "What was formed when plants that grew millions of years ago, died and were trapped and compressed under rocks",
    "id": "3edac25c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Coal"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "State three differences between animal and plant cells.",
    "id": "1e6d7a0a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Plant cells have chloroplasts, permanent vacuole and cellulose cell wall. Animal cells do not"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Why do sodium ions and chlorine ions form an ionic bond?",
    "id": "282b5fee-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "There is an electrostatic force of attraction between oppositely charged ions"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "Name an effect of climate change",
    "id": "3ef2ad4a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Increased flooding, changes in rainfall patterns, frequency of storms, amount of water in a habitat etc..."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Balance the equation: Al^3+^ + e^-^ --> Al",
    "id": "3154c786-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Al^3+^ + 3e^-^ = 3Al"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Sort the following into abiotic and biotic factors: soil pH, availability of food, oxygen availability, wind intensity, new competitors, carbon dioxide levels",
    "id": "3bdb0800-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Ab: soil pH, CO~2~ levels, O~2~ availability, wind intensity; Bio: food availability, new competitors"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What is the magnetic energy store?",
    "id": "22525744-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Energy stored in magnets that are attracting or repelling"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Give a behavioural adaptation of penguins.",
    "id": "3ca14eb6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Huddling"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "A value with magnitude only is a ________?",
    "id": "299ab4d8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "scalar"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "The tendency of objects to continue in their state of rest or of uniform motion is known as …",
    "id": "2a513f82-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "inertia"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "Which particles are located in the atoms nucleus",
    "id": "36476686-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "protons, neutrons"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name one symptom of diabetes.",
    "id": "3443a782-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Excess urine/Feeling thirsty/Lack energy/Lose weight/Fatigue"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "Draw a longitudinal wave and label the wavelength",
    "id": "3afa0486-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Explain why gold and silver can be found naturally in the Earth's crust",
    "id": "30707ca2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "It is very unreactive"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What is a positive result for starch test?",
    "id": "24cb8888-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Starch turns iodine from brown-red to blue-black"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "The distance a vehicle travels which the driver is breaking is the …",
    "id": "29fe4a20-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "breaking distance"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "How does humidity affect rate of transpiration?",
    "id": "27b8e16c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Higher humidity decreases rate"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name the organ that secretes adrenaline.",
    "id": "3459799a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Adrenal gland"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Suggest 3 ways in which a hospital can reduce the spread of antibiotic-resistant strains.",
    "id": "38377d46-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Only use antibiotics if really needed; Use strain-specific antibiotics; Maintain high hygiene standards (eg. wash hands between patient visits); Isolate patients infected with resistant strain; Visitors wash hands as they enter and leave"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "List the EM spectrum from long to short wavelength.",
    "id": "3b11aad2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Radio, microwave, infrared, visible, UV, X-rays, gamma"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "How many electrons can go in the first shell?",
    "id": "1f928916-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "2"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name three key internal conditions that need to be controlled through homeostasis.",
    "id": "33f3f908-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Temperature; Water levels; Blood glucose level"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "Give two uses of IR radiation",
    "id": "3ba76dd8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "electrical heaters, infrared cameras"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What is a genotype?",
    "id": "37c221e0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The genetic makeup of an organism for a particular gene (e.g. RR)."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What will be the products for the electrolysis of molten zinc oxide?",
    "id": "315f7d5c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Zinc and oxygen"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "How is a gene “cut out” from the genome of one species and inserted the genome of another?",
    "id": "38066594-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Using enzymes."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "At which electrode would Zn_+(aq) turn into Zn(s)?",
    "id": "310ffda4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Cathode (needs to gain electrons)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "State a drawback to selective breeding.",
    "id": "37fd22a4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Inbreeding – some breeds are prone to disease or inherited defects (e.g. some pugs have breathing problems)."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "What charge will an ion of fluorine take?",
    "id": "280d5350-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "1- (7 electrons in the outer shell, needs to gain one)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Explain in terms of electrons what occurs when sodium bonds with oxygen",
    "id": "2828dcb0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Two electrons transferred to an oxygen atom from two different sodium atoms"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "How are the subatomic particles arranged in an atom?",
    "id": "1f72f27c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Protons and neutrons in the nucleus, electrons orbiting in shells"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Give one impact on the environment by removing hedgrows.",
    "id": "3ea468ba-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Soil erosion / Reduce soil fertility"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "Balance the equation: Li + H~2~O = LiOH + H~2~",
    "id": "21cdd726-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "2Li + 2H~2~O = 2LiOH + H~2~"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Draw the circuit symbol for a switch",
    "id": "2d0e2a50-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "State Newton's First Law",
    "id": "2a4507f8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The velocity of an object will only change if a resultant force is acting on the object."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Describe the cells produced by meiosis.",
    "id": "369a8596-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "4 cells, genetically different."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the carcinogen in tobacco smoke.",
    "id": "27e2a902-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Tar"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Draw the I-V characteristic for a diode",
    "id": "2e0a5cda-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C3 Quantitative Chemistry",
    "question": "What is the unit for concentration? (Double only)",
    "id": "2d0416c8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "g/dm^3^"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "List 4 energy stores.",
    "id": "2224dfc6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Four from: chemical, kinetic, gravitational potential, elastic potential, internal/thermal, nuclear, magnetic, electrostatic."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What is the difference between correlation and causal mechanism?",
    "id": "27c83ca2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Correlation: A link between two; Causal: One thing leads to the other"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "The green and yellow wire in a plug is the ________",
    "id": "2dcc3a72-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "earth"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "What are the products of complete combustion?",
    "id": "398d1e76-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Carbon dioxide and water"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What are carbohydrates made up of?",
    "id": "22b5e836-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Simple sugars"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "What is an element?",
    "id": "1f613b22-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A substance made of only one type of atom"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "How does carbon get from the air into plants?",
    "id": "3ce86486-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Photosynthesis"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "How are artificial hearts used to treat patients with a damaged heart?",
    "id": "258b993e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A temporary treatment while waiting for heart transplant"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Root hair cells have lots of mitochondria to release energy. What is the energy used for?",
    "id": "1ea247a8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Active transport of mineral ions into root hair cells"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "State three effects of global warming.",
    "id": "3e5426a2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Climate change / Ice caps melt / Warming seas dissolve less carbon dioxide"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "State three concerns around genetically engineering plants.",
    "id": "38102ec6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "1. Unknown effects on populations of wild flowers"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "What is the EM radiation with the highest frequency?",
    "id": "3b0d0752-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Gamma"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "Which drug originated from willow?",
    "id": "2cd79706-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Aspirin"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Explain why a higher temperature results in faster diffusion.",
    "id": "1ec1554e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "More kinetic energy, particles move around more"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Give two examples of what nanoparticles can be used for",
    "id": "29982772-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Medical applications, sun creams, catalysts, deoderants, cosmetics, electronics"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "The places on a magnet where the magnetic forces are the strongest are called the…",
    "id": "404be6c0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "poles"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "Explain why sodium is less reactive than caesium (3 marks)",
    "id": "21e9b144-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Fewer shells/electrons, less shielding (or stronger attraction from nucleus), harder to lose electrons"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C5 Energy Changes",
    "question": "If the reactants have more energy than the products, what kind of a reaction must have taken place?",
    "id": "31999abe-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "An exothermic one. The missing energy has been transferred to the surroundings."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "The average kinetic energy of particles is known as the ___________",
    "id": "31d0bac6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "temperature"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "State the three ways in which white blood cells defend the body.",
    "id": "2cb9c546-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Engulf pathogens + Produce antibodies + Produce antitoxins"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "What type of magnet loses its magnetism when it is removed from a magnetic field?",
    "id": "408d3328-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "induced magnet"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C10 Using resources",
    "question": "Why is it important to reduce use, recycle and and reuse products?",
    "id": "4043cd78-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Reduces the use of limited resources, energy sources and environmental impacts"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "Give one importance of respiration.",
    "id": "2e590772-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Metabolic reactions (eg. Build)/Muscle contraction/Mainting body temp/Active transport"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "Describe the wavelength of radiation that is reemitted back off the Earth",
    "id": "3ee47482-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Long Wave"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "How is the fossil record helpful?",
    "id": "381e294a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "It shows how much organisms have changed and developed over time, and can show the environment and climate then"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What is a genome?",
    "id": "36b077d4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The entire genetic material of an organism."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "Balance the equation: K + H~2~O = KOH + H~2~",
    "id": "21d06cca-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "2K + 2H~2~O = 2KOH + H~2~"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Define 'biomass'.",
    "id": "3cba6022-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Amount of biological material in an organism (without water)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "Suggest three factors that affect health.",
    "id": "2a5b1eda-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Diet/Stress/life situations (eg. Hygiene)/pathogens/immune system"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What is evolution?",
    "id": "37ef1fec-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A change in the inherited characteristics of a population over time through a process of natural selection which may result in the formation of a new species."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What is the formula of calcium chloride?",
    "id": "30d56c70-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "CaCl_"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Suggest two alternative power source that reduces air pollution.",
    "id": "3e352cac-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Low-sulphur fuels / Biofuels / Renewable energy"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Why do we use the binomial naming system?",
    "id": "394ba856-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Every organisms' names would vary in different languages, but Latin is considered to be the old common language in which everyone can use/understand"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "What is the approximate proportion of nitrogen in Earth's current atmopshere?",
    "id": "3eb48a9c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "80%"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Why do animals that live in hot climates adapt to have a high SA:V ratio?",
    "id": "3c9c5dc0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Increase heat loss"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "What is the range of alpha radiation in air?",
    "id": "3658dc4a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "short - 5 cm in air"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "What is a hypertonic solution?",
    "id": "1ed7afb0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A solution with a higher solute conc than the cell"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What is a reliable energy source",
    "id": "225c6400-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "one which can produce energy all the time."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Where do you get adult stem cells in animals?",
    "id": "1f4d69ee-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Bone marrow"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Why is sodium not produced in the electrolysis of sodium chloride solution?",
    "id": "3171cc8c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "It is more reactive than hydrogen so hydrogen is produced instead."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Name the structure formed by fertilisation (fusion of male and female gametes).",
    "id": "3682f50c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Zygote"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Write the equation showing the reaction between H^+^ and OH^-^ ions",
    "id": "30a66d26-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "H^+^ + OH^-^ = H~2~O"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Outline the flow of air from the atmosphere into our lungs, starting from the nasal cavity.",
    "id": "258e147a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Nasal cavity --> trachea --> bronchi --> bronchioles --> alveoli"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What are some advantages of tidal energy?",
    "id": "227cbd7c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "No carbon dioxide produced."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What is the name of the process in which the nucleus of an atom splits?",
    "id": "224fdbd6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "fisssion"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "Where can Salmonella bacteria be found?",
    "id": "2c7de47c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Raw meat, chicken, eggs"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "Name three greenhouse gases",
    "id": "3edfac9a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Water Vapour, Carbon Dioxide and Methane"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "Name two non-renewable energy resources",
    "id": "22576b1c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Fossil fuels, nuclear fuel"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "State the equation which links acceleration, mass and resultant force",
    "id": "29cf5e18-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "F = ma"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Describe the state of the diaphragm as we breathe out.",
    "id": "2595bf0e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Relaxes and return to dome shape"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "How are the nutrients carried away from the gut?",
    "id": "2520fc28-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Absorbed into bloodstream through small intestine"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "Distance an speed are examples of _________ quantities",
    "id": "299fa9a2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "scalar"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Which organ produces thyroxine?",
    "id": "344f8872-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Thyroid gland"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Explain why graphite can act as a lubricant",
    "id": "286ba2d4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Weak forces between layers which are free to slide over each other"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "For a cube with sides length 2nm, calculate the surface area to volume ratio",
    "id": "2993397e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "24:8 = 3:1"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Define 'malignant tumours'.",
    "id": "27d2125e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Tumours that invade other tissues and can spread to other parts of the body through blood to form secondary tumours"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "How does viscosity change with the length of an alkane?",
    "id": "397838bc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The longer the alkane, the more viscous (the thicker) it is"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "What is the formula for a mean rate of reaction in terms of reactants?",
    "id": "34b36f54-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "quantity of reactant used/time taken"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "What state is bromine at room temperature?",
    "id": "21c8e194-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "liquid"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "The level of adrenaline is controlled by a negative feedback system. True or false?",
    "id": "345c14f2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "FALSE"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Define 'denaturation'.",
    "id": "24ef8eea-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Loss of active site"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "Draw the magnetic field around a bar magnet",
    "id": "40948df8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name the two coordination centres that make up the central nervous system.",
    "id": "340c1e34-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Brain + Spinal cord"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C5 Energy Changes",
    "question": "How does the law of conservation of energy apply to chemistry?",
    "id": "317c7a6a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "In all chemical reactions, energy is either transferred to the surroundings or from the surroundings."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name the component in the nervous system that bring about responses to stimuli.",
    "id": "33fad188-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Effectors"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "What charge will an ion of barium take?",
    "id": "280ada26-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "2+ (group 2 so two electrons in the outer shell, needs to lose them both)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "Chemical energy is stored as…?",
    "id": "222c6fde-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "chemicals waiting to react"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "Oscillations are along the same direction as the direction of travel is a _________ wave",
    "id": "3adc2ac4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "longitudinal"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C8 Chemical Analysis",
    "question": "In chromatography why must the solvent height be lower than the pencil line?",
    "id": "3ac3af30-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "So that the substances do not dissolve into the solvent off the paper"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C8 Chemical Analysis",
    "question": "In everyday language what is a \"pure\" substance?",
    "id": "39a738c4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A substance that has had nothing added to it and is in its \"natural\" state"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name the hormone secreted by the pituitary gland that controls the production of thyroxine?",
    "id": "34541d74-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "TSH (thyroid stimulating hormone)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "Energy stored within moving objects is __________",
    "id": "31c752ce-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "kinetic"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Is this process oxidation or reduction? Al = Al^3+^ + 3e^-^",
    "id": "30e59f82-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Oxidation"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "How do producers make biomass?",
    "id": "3cbf5546-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "By doing photosynthesis"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C5 Energy Changes",
    "question": "Is making bonds endothermic or exothermic?",
    "id": "31a133be-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Exothermic. Energy is released when chemical bonds are formed (like how two magnets move together when close and generate kinetic energy)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "Changes of state are caused by the amount of _________ a substance has",
    "id": "31b888ac-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "energy"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "What colour is the neutral wire in a three core cable?",
    "id": "2dc3057e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "blue"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "A value with magnitude and direction is a ____________?",
    "id": "299d314a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "vector"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "When does incomplete combustion occur?",
    "id": "398f65a0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "When there is not enough oxygen present"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name a complex carbohydrate that is made up of glucose.",
    "id": "24b28586-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Starch/Cellulose/Glycogen"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What is the electrostatic energy store?",
    "id": "2254e1a8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Energy stored n electric charges that are attracting or repelling"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C10 Using resources",
    "question": "What are finite resources?",
    "id": "400b2fcc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Resources that will run out"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "What is fractional distillation?",
    "id": "397cd84a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A process used to separate mixtures of substances with different boiling points"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "How does carbon monoxide cause an effect in our body?",
    "id": "3e309a7a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Binds to haemoglobin irreversibly --> less Hb available to bind to oxygen --> suffocation"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C5 Energy Changes",
    "question": "Give two examples of exothermic reactions.",
    "id": "318105c6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Combustion, respiration"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What is the formula of aluminium nitrate?",
    "id": "30d83a54-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Al(NO_)_"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Briefly describe how tobacco smoke causes lung infection.",
    "id": "27e4f4be-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Stops cilia from working, excess mucus (trapping bacteria in lungs)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "What is equilibrium?",
    "id": "34e76c1e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The point in a reversible reaction when the forward and reverse reactions are occurring at the same rate"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Draw the circuit symbol for an ammeter",
    "id": "2d2a6170-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "What are the risks of exposure to gamma rays?",
    "id": "3bc15b30-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Gamma rays are ionising so can cause mutations which may result in cancer"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Define reduction in the context of loss and gain of electrons",
    "id": "307cd538-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Reduction is the gain of electrons"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "What was formed when shells of organisms made using dissolved carbon dioxide, fell to the bottom of the ocean and were covered and compressed",
    "id": "3ed7d5f6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Sedimentary rock"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C10 Using resources",
    "question": "What are the four stages in a product's life cycle?",
    "id": "40412ce4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Extracting and processing raw materials, manufacturing and packaging, use and operation, disposal"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "A battery is a store of __________ energy.",
    "id": "222f0550-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "chemical"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Name the cell that keeps phloem alive.",
    "id": "1eb4a39e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Companion cells"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Briefly explain an adaptation of spongy mesophyll tissue in plants.",
    "id": "279d1d2e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Big air spaces and large surface area for efficient gas diffusion"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "What isa  molecule?",
    "id": "1f66b6b0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A substance made of more than one atom chemically bonded together (can be atoms of the same type!)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "A typical reaction time is …",
    "id": "2a0328e2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "0.2-0.9 s"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "What is gamma radiation?",
    "id": "36556448-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "electromagnetic wave (NOT a particle)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Draw the circuit symbol for a resistor",
    "id": "2d1b0004-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "What is a contact force?",
    "id": "29a49a0c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A force between two object which are touching"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Where does differentiation of stem cells occur in humans?",
    "id": "1f3b06c8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Bone marrow"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "What is the unit of current?",
    "id": "2dfb0fb4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Amps (A)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C8 Chemical Analysis",
    "question": "How can oxygen be tested for?",
    "id": "3ac86070-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Relights a glowing splint"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Prokaryotes have a cell wall. True or false?",
    "id": "1e79ebc8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "TRUE"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "What will happen to a plant cell if it is in a hypotonic solution?",
    "id": "1eed5c84-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Water enters cell --> turgid"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Explain why pure metals are soft",
    "id": "2986d4ea-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Layers of metal ions are free to slide over each other"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Explain the use of a tail in sperm cells.",
    "id": "1e908946-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "To swim and move around (to reach the egg)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Suggest one adaptation that thermophiles have to help them live in high temperatures.",
    "id": "3c1461e0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Special enzymes with higher optimal temp (don't denature at high temp)/Specially structured cell membrane and/or cell wall"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Suggest a possible challenge in breeding programmes.",
    "id": "3ea9b298-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Animals do not reproduce easily or fast / Must avoid inbreeding / No natural habitats for them to return to"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name the hormone that causes egg maturation in the ovaries.",
    "id": "34659e78-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "FSH (follicle stimulating hormone)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Complete the sentence: In covalent bonds, electrons are _______________________",
    "id": "28581368-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Shared"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "Name an example of a transverse wave",
    "id": "3ad97c66-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "light, water, any electromagnetic"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "How can we use Agrobacterium tumefaciens in plants?",
    "id": "2c99020c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "They cause galls --> genetic manipulation"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State a hazard in doing food tests.",
    "id": "24dcb658-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Ethanol is flammable/Biuret is corrosive"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name a treatment for type 1 diabetes but not type 2 diabetes.",
    "id": "34486114-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Insulin injection"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "The brown wire in a plug is the _______",
    "id": "2dc7a19c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "live"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name a barrier method of contraception.",
    "id": "34897410-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Condom/Diaphragm"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "State the function of the mitochondria.",
    "id": "1e614ac8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Site of aerobic respiration, releasing energy"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "The change of an objects speed in a given time is the _________",
    "id": "2a150a80-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "acceleration"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Under what sort of situation would adrenaline be released?",
    "id": "345e7346-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "In reaction to fear or stress"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "What factors can affect the rate of a reaction?",
    "id": "34c15e0c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Temperature, surface area of a solid, concentration or reactants in solution, pressure of gases"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Based on what knowledge were the three domains set?",
    "id": "395077aa-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Different biochemistry of cell and ribosomes, and how cells reproduce differently"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What are the units of energy?",
    "id": "21eeb37e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "joules"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What does (aq) stand for?",
    "id": "3088c096-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Aqueous: when something is dissolved in water. E.g. NaCl(aq) is salt water"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "Mechanical working  is…?",
    "id": "220fc9b0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The energy transfer when a force moves through a distance"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "Give the name for the magnet created using a coil of wire",
    "id": "40980546-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "solenoid"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "What are the units of acceleration?",
    "id": "29ea79aa-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "metres per second squared (m/s^2^)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What is the name of the energy transfer pathway when a charge moves?",
    "id": "221561d6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "electrical working"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Explain why ionic compounds conduct electricity when molten",
    "id": "28496bd8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Because the ions are free to move"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name the hormone that maintains the uterus lining.",
    "id": "346c8f8a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Progesterone"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "Particles wich are further apart have _________ potential energy",
    "id": "31cc2470-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "more"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "How many bonds does each carbon have in diamond?",
    "id": "285f6686-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "4"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Define 'cloning'.",
    "id": "1f406e4c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Production of identical offspring by asexual reproduction/mitosis"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "State the function of the ribosomes.",
    "id": "1e63c802-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Site of protein synthesis"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "What is the name given to the increasing average temperature of the Earth?",
    "id": "3ef05e46-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Climate Change"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C5 Energy Changes",
    "question": "What happens to the temperature of the surroundings during an endothermic reaction?",
    "id": "318abaee-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "They decrease. The thermometer is included in \"the surroundings\" so shows the temperature decreasing."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Why does the potato skin needs to be removed before putting the potato cylinders into the solutions?",
    "id": "1ef206ee-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Skin is impermeable"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C10 Using resources",
    "question": "How is sewage treated?",
    "id": "402b44e2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Screening, sedimentation, anaerobic digestion, aerobic biological treatment"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What is the name for the positive electrode?",
    "id": "3105677c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The anode"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What is the effect of nicotine in tobacco smoke?",
    "id": "27e066d8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Addictiveness"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What are some advantages of nuclear fuel?",
    "id": "226164a0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "No carbon dioxide produced, reliable."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "State one method of screening embryos.",
    "id": "37de69d6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Amniocentesis/Chorionic villus sampling/IVF"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "For animals that living in cold climates, would they have adaptations to increase or decrease their surface area to volume ratio?",
    "id": "3c99f530-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Decrease"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "Viral diseases can be cured. True or false?",
    "id": "2c7863da-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "FALSE"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "If something has gained electrons, what charge will it have?",
    "id": "280fce32-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Negative"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "The strength of magnetic field surrounding a conducting wire depends on…",
    "id": "40c9c05e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Size of current and distance from wire"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "As decomposers break down organic material, what is released into the air? How does it return to organisms?",
    "id": "3cd7234c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Carbon dioxide --> taken into producers for photosynthesis"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "How does gonorrhoea spread?",
    "id": "2c8eebb4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Sexual contact"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "State the effect on increasing the pressure of a gas on the rate of reaction",
    "id": "34cccc7e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Increases"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "How does tobacco mosaic virus affect the plants?",
    "id": "2c7257a6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Destroy chloroplasts, so reduce photosynthesis"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "Why would photosynthetic rate decrease at higher temperatures?",
    "id": "2e451c4e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Enzymes become denatured"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C8 Chemical Analysis",
    "question": "How can hydrogen be tested for?",
    "id": "3ac5ff60-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Makes a squeaky pop when a splint is placed in it"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Current which flows in one direction is…?",
    "id": "2e1c244c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "direct current"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "State the melting points of ionic substances",
    "id": "283580d2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "High"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Which ions are in CaCO~3~",
    "id": "30c98c7a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Ca^2+^ and CO~3~^2+^"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What is the positive result for sugars?",
    "id": "24d0629a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Benedict's solution turn from clear blue to brick-red (precipitate)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "The process taking place when a wave bounces off of a surface",
    "id": "3aedbe4c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "reflection"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Give one characteristic of a lion that makes it a good competitor.",
    "id": "3bece0d4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Sharp teeth/claws"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "All substances are made up of…?",
    "id": "34fa9474-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "atoms"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "Explain why the group 1 elements are called alkali metals",
    "id": "21d883ce-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "They are metals that form alkalis when they react with water"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "What is the unit of distance?",
    "id": "29e05dc6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "meters (m)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Genes determine the phenotype of an organism – true or false?",
    "id": "37e55084-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "False – the environment also plays a role."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Balance the equation: Cl^-^ --> Cl~2~ + e^-^",
    "id": "3157afdc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "2Cl^-^ = Cl~2~ + 2e^-^"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name the process where a matured egg is released from the ovaries.",
    "id": "34631bb2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Ovulation"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Name three acidic gases released from burning fossil fuels.",
    "id": "3e19485c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Carbon dioxide + sulphur dioxide + Nitric oxides"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State a risk factor for non-communicable diseases.",
    "id": "27ca952e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Lifestyle, substance present in body/environment"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Briefly describe the arrangement of xylem and phloem in the stem of a plant.",
    "id": "279f9590-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Organised in bundles, with xylem on the inside and phloem on the outside"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "Can EM waves travel through space?",
    "id": "3b13feb8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "yes"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "Which gases are produced when nitrogen and oxygen react in the very high temperatures of a car engine?",
    "id": "3ffbd4e6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "oxides of nitrogen"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What is a natural pacemaker?",
    "id": "2586f0d2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A group of cells in the right atrium that controls the resting heart rate"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "Name one use of glucose in plants.",
    "id": "2e478542-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Respiration / make and strenghten cellulose cell wall / make starch for storage / make lipids as energy store"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C10 Using resources",
    "question": "Name two new ways of extracting copper from low-grade ores",
    "id": "402e6c30-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Phytomining and bioleaching"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "An example of alternating current is…?",
    "id": "2e196752-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "mains electricity"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the large vessel that brings deoxygenated blood back into the heart.",
    "id": "2566e80a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Vena cava"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Draw the circuit symbol for a closed switch",
    "id": "2d10b55e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "How does concentration difference affect the rate of diffusion?",
    "id": "1ebed4c2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Higher conc difference/Steeper conc gradient --> faster diffusion"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What are lipids made up of?",
    "id": "24ba2cfa-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "1 glycerol + 3 fatty acids"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C3 Quantitative Chemistry",
    "question": "What are the four state symbols and what do they stand for?",
    "id": "2cf33d6c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "(s) solid (l) liquid (g) gas (aq) aqueous"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What is the name for the negative anode?",
    "id": "3108113e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The cathode"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Which ions are in Mg(OH)~2~",
    "id": "30cbe218-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Mg^2+^ and 2 ions of OH^-^"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "What are the risks of exposure to UV radiation?",
    "id": "3bbc536a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Premature skin aging, increased risk of skin cancer"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "How can AIDS be treated?",
    "id": "2c6add0a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Antiretrovial drugs to control (not cure) it"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Is this process oxidation or reduction? Fe - 2e^-^ = Fe~2+~",
    "id": "30edeb06-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Oxidation"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "How can AIDS be spread?",
    "id": "2c685fda-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Sexual contact; Exchange of bodily fluids (shared needles, blood transfusion)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What term is used to describe energy becoming spread out or transferred to a \"wasted\" store?",
    "id": "228bd5e6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "dissipation"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "How many chromosomes are in one human body cell?",
    "id": "1f185876-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "46"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "State one adaptations cells may have if they need to carry out active transport.",
    "id": "1efe4d78-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Lots of mitochondria for respiration for energy"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "State three methods to maintain biodiversity.",
    "id": "3e9f443e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Breeding programmes / Protect and regenerate rare habitats / Grow hedgrows / Reduce deforestation and CO~2~ emission / Recycling"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What is the type of energy transferred when a force moves through a distance?",
    "id": "220d4e4c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Mechanical transfer"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Which organs produce proteases?",
    "id": "2514b3dc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Stomach, pancreas, small intestine"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "Describe the wavelength of radiation that comes from the sun",
    "id": "3ee20dd2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Short Wave"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "What are the four things that plants compete for?",
    "id": "3bfbdc38-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Light, space, water, mineral ions"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Define 'resolution'.",
    "id": "1e44166a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The ability to distinguish between two separate points that are very close together"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State the function of xylem.",
    "id": "27a20bae-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Transports water and mineral ions from roots to other parts of the plants"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Define 'organ'.",
    "id": "229d0046-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A group of tissues working together for specific functions"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "Which gas is produced when fuels are burned and contain the impurity sulfur?",
    "id": "3efc305e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "sulfur dioxide"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Which domain tends to include most extremophiles?",
    "id": "3c0f8210-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Archaea"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C8 Chemical Analysis",
    "question": "In paper chromatography, what is the stationary phase and what is the mobile phase",
    "id": "3ab80c02-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Paper is stationary, solvent (usually water or ethanol) is mobile"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "How can you measure the quantity of a reactant or product?",
    "id": "34b8107c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "In grams or in cm_"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What is the double circulatory system?",
    "id": "2561c0b4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "One part carries blood between heart and lungs; the other carries blood between heart and other organs"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "In Flemming's LH rule, the thumb gives the direction of …",
    "id": "40a9abc0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Force"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What are proteins made up of?",
    "id": "24c16858-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Amino acids"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What are the three rules of writing a binomial scientific name of a species?",
    "id": "39495db2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "First letter of the genus should be in capital; First letter of the species should be in small letter; Both need to be in italics when printed or underlined when hand-written"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Name a structure in the body that is adapted to increase diffusion rate.",
    "id": "1ec89dfe-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Alveoli, villi"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Where does the genetic material of a prokaryotic cell exist?",
    "id": "1e7ee57e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Cytoplasm"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "For the extraction of which metals is electrolysis needed?",
    "id": "31621fee-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Ones more reactive than carbon, e.g. aluminium"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "Name five fuels we obtain from crude oil",
    "id": "39863d86-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Petrol, diesel, kerosene, heavy fuel oil and liquefied petroleum gases"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "Give one example of a metabolic reaction in cells.",
    "id": "30627d5a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Convert glucose to glycogen, starch, cellulose / make lipids / proteins / respiration / photosynthesis / breakdown of proteins"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the type of enzyme that digests lipids.",
    "id": "250d3486-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Lipases"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "Apart from light and carbon dioxide concentration, name one other limiting factor of photosynthetic rate.",
    "id": "2e42a3ec-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Temperature/Chlorophyll levels"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Describe and explain how predator population changes as prey population decreases.",
    "id": "3ccaf8a6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Predator population decreases, as less prey/food available, more predators die"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "True or false – does the theory of evolution by natural selection state that all living things evolved from simple life forms more than three billion years ago?",
    "id": "37f19e52-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "True."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "Energy stored in the nuclei of atoms is in the __________ store.",
    "id": "22486ffe-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "nuclear"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Which language does the binomial naming system use?",
    "id": "3944c09a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Latin"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What is produced at the anode and cathode in the electrolysis of aluminium oxide?",
    "id": "3169fb6a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Aluminium at the cathode and oxygen at the anode"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Briefly explain why low light intensity may decrease animal populations.",
    "id": "3bd86442-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Less light, less photosynthesis by plants --> poor plant growth --> less plant availble for animals to eat --> less herbivores grow and survive --> further affects higher levels in the food chain"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Name the type of organism that decomposes dead material.",
    "id": "3cd4acd4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Microorganisms"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Why does the anode need to be replaced in the electrolysis of aluminium oxide?",
    "id": "316c941a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The oxygen reacts with the carbon electrode to produce carbon dioxide."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "What is a molecule?",
    "id": "2875ec12-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A group of atoms chemically bonded together"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C3 Quantitative Chemistry",
    "question": "Calculate the M~r~ of H~2~SO~4~",
    "id": "2cf7e290-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "98"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Define 'diffusion'.",
    "id": "1eb70d8c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Net movement of particles from an area of high to low concentration (down concentration gradient)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What is electrolysis?",
    "id": "31003f0e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Using electricity to break down a substance"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What is the definition of power?",
    "id": "2200c7b2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Power is the rate of transfer of energy or the rate of doing work"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Describe how a muscle cell is adapted for its function.",
    "id": "1e9fbbaa-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Special proteins for contraction; Many mitochondria for energy; Store glycogen to release glucose for respiration"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "What device is used to measure weight?",
    "id": "29b159ae-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A newtonmeter"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "What is the rate of a chemical reaction in terms of reactants?",
    "id": "34ae98f8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "How quickly the reactants in a reaction are used up"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Define 'embryo'.",
    "id": "1f4859f4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A ball of cells made from mitosis of zygote"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "What is crude oil formed from?",
    "id": "396333ae-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The remains of ancient biomass (mostly plankton) that was buried in mud"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Magnesium carbonate is insoluble. What do you need to do before it will conduct electricity?",
    "id": "2850d1ac-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Melt it"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Describe the cells produced by mitosis.",
    "id": "369d1acc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "2 cells, genetically identical (clones)."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State one disease caused by long-term heavy drinking.",
    "id": "27f66a6e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Liver cirrhosis/Liver cancer/Brain damage"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "How does smog affect our health?",
    "id": "3e2c0e88-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Inhaling particulates damages our lungs and cardiovascular systems"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Describe the adaptations of a nerve cell.",
    "id": "1e983ac4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Lots of dendrites; Long axon"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Convert 5mm to �m.",
    "id": "1e728860-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "5000�m"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "State the function of the cytoplasm.",
    "id": "1e5c24bc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Site for chemical reactions to take place"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "What produced the gases present in Earth's early atmosphere?",
    "id": "3ec1f4a2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Volcanoes"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Name the process where water escapes into the ocean through gaps between soil and rocks.",
    "id": "3ce0e4b8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Percolation"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the blood vessel type that carries blood from the organs back to the heart.",
    "id": "255255f2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Vein"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "What colour is the live wire in a three core cable?",
    "id": "2dc0b7ec-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "brown"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "How does alpha decay alter the mass number of the parent nucleus?",
    "id": "367012a2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "decreases by 4"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State the function of phloem.",
    "id": "27a77b5c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Transports dissolved sugars from leaves to the rest of the plant"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State one adaptation of the lungs for efficient gas exchange.",
    "id": "259a9ae2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Lots of alveoli to increase surface area; Rich blood supply/Extensive capillary network; Thin walls (one cell thick)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What is an allele?",
    "id": "36b75ae0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A different version of a gene."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "What is a mixture?",
    "id": "1f693c00-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A substance made of more than one thing not chemically bonded together"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "Why doesn't temperature increase during melting?",
    "id": "31edabd6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Energy is being used to weaken forces between particles"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "How does the stomach defend the body against pathogens?",
    "id": "2cb7417c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Hydrochloric acid destroys microorganisms in mucus/food"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "The national grid consists of…?",
    "id": "2e2565c0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Cables and transformers"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "What happens to the glycogen stored in muscles when you exercise?",
    "id": "2e5e5e16-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Converted into glucose for respiration"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the type of enzyme that digests proteins.",
    "id": "2505d056-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Proteases"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "What is more reactive, chlorine or bromine?",
    "id": "21b6b9ce-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Chlorine"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Define 'population'.",
    "id": "3bce1640-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A group of organisms of one species that interbreed and live in the same place at the same time"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Is polydactyly a dominant or recessive condition?",
    "id": "37d2f042-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Dominant."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "State the three key steps in meiosis.",
    "id": "369f8758-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "1. Copies of the DNA are made, 2. The cell divides twice to form 4 gametes, each with a single set of chromosomes. 3. All 4 cells are genetically different from each other."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "Sound in air travels at …",
    "id": "2a4219ee-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "330 m/s"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C10 Using resources",
    "question": "What needs to be removed from sewage and agrictultural waste water?",
    "id": "40261db4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Organic matter and harmful microbes"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "Name the pigment in chloroplasts that absorbs light.",
    "id": "2e3b7932-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Chlorophyll"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Apart from digestion, what is another function of hydrochloric acid in the stomach?",
    "id": "252ab9a2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Kill pathogens in food"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "State the function of the nucleus.",
    "id": "1e595160-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Controls all activities of the cell, contains genetic information"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the blood vessel type that is found within organs that link arteries and veins.",
    "id": "2554c86e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Capillaries"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Name a toxic gas that is released from incomplete combustion.",
    "id": "3e2e4dba-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Carbon monoxide"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "Why do plants need nitrates for good growth?",
    "id": "2e4a4ebc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Make proteins"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Why do atoms transfer electrons in ionic bonding?",
    "id": "281c5dd2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "So that they can have full outer shells"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What happens to an ionic substance when it is melted or dissolved in water?",
    "id": "3102e04c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The ions become free to move around"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "What is the unit for resistance?",
    "id": "2e009f6a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Ohms (Ω)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "What two methods can you use to obesrve the field around a bar magnet?",
    "id": "40bdbdcc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Iron filings or plotting compass"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Where does protein digestion occur?",
    "id": "251c1a28-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Stomach + Small intestine"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "What are the two types of cracking?",
    "id": "39990f9c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Catalytic and steam cracking"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "What is anaerobic respiration?",
    "id": "2e60b882-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Breakdown of glucose to release small amount of energy without the use of oxygen"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What are some advantages of wave power?",
    "id": "2281871c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "No carbon dioxide produced"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Which ions are in NH~4~OH",
    "id": "30d0be6e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "NH~4~^+^ and OH^-^"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "A typical running speed is …",
    "id": "2a3d4216-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "3 m/s"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "What is a gene?",
    "id": "1f12b236-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A short section of DNA that codes for a protein/controls a characteristic"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What are red blood cells?",
    "id": "253e7c3a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Biconcave cells that have haemoglobin - carry oxygen"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "Explain why the noble gases are inert",
    "id": "21bbb1e0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "They have full outer shells, so do not need to gain or lose electrons"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "The force exerted by gas on a surface as the particles collide with it is known as….?",
    "id": "31dcc370-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "gas pressure"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the equipment used to estimate transpiration rate.",
    "id": "27c0b856-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Potometer"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Define 'concentrated'.",
    "id": "1ed0619c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A solution with a low water conc, but high solute conc"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the product of the breakdown of proteins.",
    "id": "250ab8dc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Amino acids"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "Give one use of microwaves",
    "id": "3b20f834-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "cooking food"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "Define atom",
    "id": "34f8423c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The smallest part of an element that can exist."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "How is the amount of reactant changing at equilibrium?",
    "id": "34e9b12c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "It is not changing"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "Why did Mendeleev leave gaps in his periodic table?",
    "id": "1fa438dc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "For elements that had not been discovered yet"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "What is the ionising power of alpha radiation?",
    "id": "3666ceae-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "very high"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name the type of neurone that carries impulses away from the central nervous system.",
    "id": "34079486-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Motor neurone"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What is an alkali?",
    "id": "3097915c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A soluble base. E.g. sodium hydroxide"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name the hormone that stimulates ovulation.",
    "id": "3467e7fa-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "LH (luteinising hormone)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What is polydactyly?",
    "id": "37d06cfa-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A condition that causes the individual to have extra fingers or toes."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "Explain why increasing the pressure of a gas increases the rate of a reaction",
    "id": "34cf5444-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Less space for the particles to move around in, therefore more frequent collisions"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "What does soluble mean?",
    "id": "284bddc8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Dissolves in water"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "In ionic bonds, electrons are ___________________",
    "id": "285a6b36-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Transferred"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "Name KOH",
    "id": "21d59ae2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Potassium hydroxide"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "State one medical/scientific benefit of therapeutic cloning.",
    "id": "1f59c93c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "No rejection problem"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C8 Chemical Analysis",
    "question": "Give three examples of formulations",
    "id": "3ab2d8d6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "fuels, cleaning agents, paints, medicines, alloys, fertilisers and foods."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State the function of the salivary glands.",
    "id": "22a1de40-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Produce digestive enzymes (eg. Amylase)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "What are extremophiles?",
    "id": "3c0d30aa-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "(micro)organisms that live in environments that are very extreme (eg. high temp, pressure, salt conc)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "How does land pollution affect our biodiversity?",
    "id": "3dfe9610-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Less (clean) food available / Loss of habitat / Global warming leading to migration"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Wasps building nests is a behaviour adaptation to compete for...?",
    "id": "3bf6f4fc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Shelter/Habitat"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Name two historic examples of selective breeding.",
    "id": "37fae2dc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "1. Breeding food crops from wild plants"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "What is photosynthesis?",
    "id": "2e38f432-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Building glucose from carbon dioxide and water using light"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "What state is iodine at room temperature?",
    "id": "21cb4fe2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "solid"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Define acid in terms of pH",
    "id": "3083ef3a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A substance with a pH of less than 7"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Explain the importance of active transport in animals.",
    "id": "1efbd37c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Cells in gut lining does AT to absorb glucose effectively from the bloodstream"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Which organ produces testosterone?",
    "id": "34713314-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Testes"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What elements make up proteins?",
    "id": "24c68856-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "C, H, O, N"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Define 'natural selection'.",
    "id": "37f6271a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The process by which evolution takes place - Nature chooses those those with favourable characteristics (best suited to environment) to survive and reproduce, passing on their genes"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "What are synapses?",
    "id": "341ecfca-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The junction/physical gap between neurones"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C10 Using resources",
    "question": "In what kinds of locations is desalination carried out?",
    "id": "4023898c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Ones where there is limited supply of fresh water"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "State the equation which links density, mass and volume",
    "id": "31a8cf98-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "_=m/v"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Suggest one adaptation that halophiles have to help them survive in salty areas.",
    "id": "3c16b8be-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Special cytoplasm to prevent water loss by osmosis/Special cell membrane/cell wall"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Which ions are in NaCl",
    "id": "30c73b78-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Na_ and Cl_"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Why do sperm cells have lots of mitochondria?",
    "id": "1e933f92-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "To provide lots of energy for swimming"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "What is the approximate proportion of oxygen in Earth's current atmopshere?",
    "id": "3eb75b3c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "20%"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What is a concentrated acid?",
    "id": "30bfd3a6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "An acid where there are lots of acid particles in the water."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Name three major greenhouse gases.",
    "id": "3e45628e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Carbon dioxide + Methane + Water vapour"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C3 Quantitative Chemistry",
    "question": "What is the conservation of mass?",
    "id": "2ce92ef8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "That atoms cannot be created or destroyed"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "Emission of radiation from an atom may lead to _____________ moving to a ______________ energy level",
    "id": "3530a758-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "electrons, lower"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "What can the period tell you about the electrons in an atom?",
    "id": "1f9edc70-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "How many shells an atom has. E.g. carbon is in the second period so has two shells"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "How is not having a nucleus good for red blood cells?",
    "id": "254b0c0c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "More space to pack more haemoglobin"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "State one effect of adrenaline.",
    "id": "3456fc88-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Increase heart rate/breathing rate/Increase glycogen conversion to glucose/Pupils dilate/Increase mental awareness/More blood flow to muscles"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name one factor that may affect human reaction time.",
    "id": "341317a2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Energy or sugary drinks/Practise beforehand etc."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Describe the structure of DNA.",
    "id": "36a6f998-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A polymer made up of two strands forming a double helix."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "How does temperature affect rate of transpiration?",
    "id": "27b662d4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Higher temp increases rate"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State a structural difference between arteries and veins.",
    "id": "25573f04-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A: thicker walls, more elastic tissue, no valves; V: thinner walls, less elastic tissues, have valves"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "State the equation which links extension, force and spring constant",
    "id": "29c7dbd4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "F=ke"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "How can bacterial diseases be treated?",
    "id": "2c9b7820-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Antibiotics"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C3 Quantitative Chemistry",
    "question": "What formula relates moles, mass and M~r~?",
    "id": "2cff273a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Moles = mass/Mr"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "Why is fractional distillation important?",
    "id": "398178f0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Because the different fractions have different uses"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "An object is said to _________ radiation when a wave can pass through the object",
    "id": "3aeb579c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "transmit"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "State the masses of the subatomic particles",
    "id": "1f6dfe98-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Protons: 1, neutrons: 1, electrons: 0"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C3 Quantitative Chemistry",
    "question": "What is a mole?",
    "id": "2cfa6682-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A number of particles"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "Force, displacement and velocity are examples of __________ quantities",
    "id": "29a225d8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "vector"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "What other uses are there for products of fractional distillation?",
    "id": "39888046-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Solvents, lubricants, polymers and detergents"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "Energy stored in objects which move.",
    "id": "22276818-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "kinetic"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Why is the ability to clone plants quickly a benefit?",
    "id": "1f5735c8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Produce large numbers of rare plants reliably and safely to stop their extinction and for research, agriculture advances"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Suggest why plants may have different root depths.",
    "id": "3c00e1d8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "To avoid competition for water and/or minerial ions at the same soil depth"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "What will happen to a plant cell if it is in an isotonic solution?",
    "id": "1eeb0ee8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "No net water movement --> flaccid"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "How are the electrons in a Magnesium atom arranged?",
    "id": "1fa93922-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "2, 8, 2002"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Why do nanoparticles have different properties to bulk materials?",
    "id": "2995bf32-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Because of their high SA:V ratio"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Draw the I-V characteristic for a fixed resistor",
    "id": "2e05710c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "Where does aerobic respiration occur in the cell?",
    "id": "2e567228-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Mitochondria"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the type of enzyme that digests carbohydrates.",
    "id": "24fe1e06-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Carbohydrases"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Give two examples of vectors used in genetic engineering.",
    "id": "380af078-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A bacterial plasmid, a virus"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "What type of salts are formed by the three main acids?",
    "id": "309f35f6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Hydrochloric acid produces chlorides, sulphuric acid = sulphates, nitric acid = nitrates"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "Draw a particle diagram for a solid",
    "id": "31e69440-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "Electrons in atoms are located in ___________",
    "id": "352c18a0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "energy levels"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "How can pathogens be spread?",
    "id": "2c5c1162-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "By air/droplet infection, direct contact, water"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "What is the name of the single point at which an object's mass appears to act?",
    "id": "29b3ca36-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "centre of mass"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "What human activities increase carbon dioxide levels?",
    "id": "3eebd20e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Deforestation and burning fossil fuels"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Define 'species'.",
    "id": "37f3e3f6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Organisms that can interbreed to produce fertile offspring."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "Why does temperature of a substance increase as it is heated?",
    "id": "31f25b86-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Particles gain more kinetic energy and temperature is a measure of kinetic energy"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "How does your skin act as a defence against pathogen entry?",
    "id": "2cb237ea-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Barrier; Antimicrobial secretions; Microorganism layer"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "How does vaccination make a person become immune to a disease?",
    "id": "2cc3ae1c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Inactive antigens in vaccine stimulates WBC to make antibodies and memory cells, which stimulates secondary response"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Explain why ionic substances have high melting points.",
    "id": "2837e6e2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Strong bonds between oppositely charged ions are hard to break"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Define 'transpiration'.",
    "id": "27aef846-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Loss of water vapour by evaporation from the leaf surface through stomata"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C5 Energy Changes",
    "question": "What happens to the temperature of the surroundings during an exothermic reaction?",
    "id": "318351a0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "They increase. The thermometer is included in \"the surroundings\" so shows the temperature increasing."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "The area around a magnet where a force acts on another magnet or magnetic material in the…",
    "id": "40509742-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Magnetic field"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "State 3 ways in which understanding of the human genome will be important.",
    "id": "36b2ca20-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "1. To search for genes linked to different types of disease, 2. To understand and treat inherited disorders,  3. To trace early human migration patterns"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "What is a trend?",
    "id": "21be2a7e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A pattern in properties"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "metal carbonate + acid = ?",
    "id": "30b0819e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "salt + water + carbon dioxide"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "In Flemming's LH rule, the second finger gives the direction of …",
    "id": "40ac5186-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Current"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Why is it difficult to develop new antibiotics to combat the appearance of new antibiotic-resistant strains of bacteria?",
    "id": "3839cc22-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The development of new antibiotics is expensive and slow (won't be able to keep up)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Why do animal cells burst in hypotonic solutions?",
    "id": "1ee65f56-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "No cell wall"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "The region in a longitudinal wave where particels are furthest apart is a…",
    "id": "3ae66016-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "rarefaction"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C3 Quantitative Chemistry",
    "question": "When a metal forms a metal oxide, why does the mass increase?",
    "id": "2cebb47a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Because oxygen atoms have been added"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "State two differences beween diffusion and osmosis.",
    "id": "1f03573c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "D: Any particles, does not need a membrane; O: Water specific, needs partially permeable membrane"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "What was formed when plankton that lived in the ocean millions of years ago, died and were trapped and compressed under rocks",
    "id": "3edd4aae-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Crude Oil and Natural Gas"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State the importance of having carbohydrates in our diet.",
    "id": "24b5331c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Energy source - Break down glucose in respiration to release energy for metabolic reactions"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What are some disadvantages of fossil fuels?",
    "id": "225ee37e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "carbon dioxide (greenhouse gas) produced leading to global warming. Can produce sulphur dioxide causing acid rain."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What are non-communicable diseases?",
    "id": "27c33978-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Non-infectious diseases"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "How big are nanoparticles?",
    "id": "2990c112-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "1-100nm, a few hundred atoms"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What are fossils?",
    "id": "38128d88-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Remains of organisms from millions of years ago that are found preserved (in rocks, ice etc.)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "Explain why increasing the concentration increases the rate of reaction",
    "id": "34ca6c7c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "More concentrated means more particles in solution, therefore more frequent collisions between reactants."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Where is the cell body found in the motor neurone?",
    "id": "3410af4e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "At the beginning of the motor neurone"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "When Earth was formed it's atmosphere was similar to which planets?",
    "id": "3ebc7efa-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Venus and Mars"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "What is a catalyst?",
    "id": "34d91d76-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Something which changes the rate of a reaction but is not used up in that reaction"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "What is the unit of weight?",
    "id": "29d409fe-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Newtons (N)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Describe the steps in which a bacteria strain develops resistance to an antibiotic.",
    "id": "382e4186-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "1. Mutation occurs in an individual bacterium within a population; 2. It survives and reproduces rapidly, making more bacteria with its resistant gene; 3. Overtime, all bacteria within the population have that gene"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "State the equation of aerobic respiration.",
    "id": "2e51b94a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Glucose + Oxygen --> Carbon dioxide + Water"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "How does alpha decay alter the atomic number of the parent nucleus?",
    "id": "367259f4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "decreases by 2"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Where does starch digestion occur?",
    "id": "2519b120-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Mouth + Small intestine"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "Give three ways of increasing the force of a solenoid.",
    "id": "40b4512e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Add iron core, increase number of coils of wire, increase current, move magnetic material closer"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P7 Magnetism and Electromagnetism",
    "question": "Draw the magnetic field between two like poles.",
    "id": "40c09e2a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State the importance of having lipids in our diet.",
    "id": "24bc8d10-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Energy store/Make up cell membranes/Steroid hormones"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "The amount of energy required to change the state of one kilogram of a substance with no change in temperature is the …?",
    "id": "31d3183e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "specific latent heat"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Name one treatment for type 2 diabetes.",
    "id": "344d4c4c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Carbohydrate-controlled diet/Lose weight/Regular exercise/Medicine"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What kind of molecule are enzymes - carbohdyrates, lipids or proteins?",
    "id": "24e41920-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Proteins"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "The radius of an atom is …?",
    "id": "34fce6de-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "0.1 nm (1 x 1010 m)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Draw the circuit symbol for a diode",
    "id": "2d18785c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "On a distance time graph the gradient is used to calculate the …",
    "id": "2a26d4d6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "speed or velocity"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "How is acid rain formed?",
    "id": "3e169544-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Acidic gases released from burning fossil fuels are dissolved in rain water"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "What are the effects of carbon monoxide?",
    "id": "3ffe7246-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "a toxic gas"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "In what form is carbon in the air?",
    "id": "3cf4ca6e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Carbon dioxide"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "What are partially permeable membranes?",
    "id": "1ed2e4da-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Membranes that only allow some types of substances to pass through"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "How does having a long axon help neurones with their function?",
    "id": "1e9d45c8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Carry electrical impulses over long distances"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "How can the spread of malaria be stopped?",
    "id": "2cafc028-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Use mosquito nets; Use insecticides; Remove standing water; Take antimalarial drugs"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "The energy needed to raise the temperature 1 kg of a material by 1^o^C is the __________",
    "id": "31ce6eec-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "specific heat capacity"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "Describe the appearance of a plant infected with tobacco mosaic virus.",
    "id": "2c6fcfc2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Mosaic pattern of discoloration on leaves"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "What is an alkane?",
    "id": "396ed718-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A hydrocarbon with only single bonds"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Current which regularly changes direction is called…",
    "id": "2e171a1a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "alternating current"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Which type of microscope has higher magnification and resolving power - Light or electron?",
    "id": "1e468c42-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Electron microscopes"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State the chemical formula of glucose.",
    "id": "22b867b4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "C6H12O6"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "Explain why the following reaction does not proceed: KBr + I_",
    "id": "21dd50ac-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Iodine is less reactive than bromine so cannot displace it"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C10 Using resources",
    "question": "Give an example of a product that can be reused",
    "id": "40466bc8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Glass"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Explain why alloys can be harder than pure metals",
    "id": "298e4cfc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Different size of atoms disturb the layers to stop them sliding over each other"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B4 Bioenergetics",
    "question": "State one response of the body to exercise.",
    "id": "2e5bc598-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Increase heart rate/breathing rate/Glycogen coverted to glucose/Increase blood flow to muscles"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What are the units of velocity?",
    "id": "21f3baf4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "metres per second"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "Can sound waves travel through space?",
    "id": "3b176134-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "no"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the vessel that brings oxygenated blood from the lungs to the heart.",
    "id": "2570c5fa-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Pulmonary vein"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "State three key importances of mitosis.",
    "id": "1f273c4c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Growth, repair, asexual reproduction"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C5 Energy Changes",
    "question": "What is an exothermic reaction?",
    "id": "317ec3ec-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A reaction where energy is transferred to the surroundings."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "State an equipment that is commonly used to investigate a population of plants in a particular area.",
    "id": "3be0563e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Quadrat"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "State the effect of increasing the temperature on the rate of reaction",
    "id": "34d2333a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Increases"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "What causes global warming?",
    "id": "3e51c664-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Too much greenhouse gases --> trap too much heat within atmosphere (enhance greenhouse effect)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C6 The Rate & Extent of Chemical Change",
    "question": "Explain why increasing the surface area increases the rate of a reaction",
    "id": "34c5e274-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "More particles are available to collide, there are therefore more frequent collisions between reactants."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B3 Infection & Response",
    "question": "Name the pathogen that causes AIDS.",
    "id": "2c65fa74-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "HIV (Human immunodefiency virus)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "State the functions of white blood cells.",
    "id": "25462cc8-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Engult pathogens, produce antibodies and antitoxins"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Explain why chlorine and fluorine form covalent bonds",
    "id": "2855a678-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "They are both non-metals"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Every organism has a scientific name using a binomial system. What does binomial mean?",
    "id": "39426dd6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Two names"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "What is plasma in the blood?",
    "id": "253c12a6-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Yellow liquid that carries blood cells, proteins and dissolved substances around the body"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What are some disadvantages of wave power?",
    "id": "2284738c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "unreliable - may not produce electricity when calm seas"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Define 'homeostasis'.",
    "id": "33f1b468-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Maintainence of internal environment relatively stable at optimum conditions through negative feedback"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What causes mass extinction? Suggest two examples of this cause.",
    "id": "3824ff68-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Single catastrophic event that also affects climate over a long period (eg. asteroid collision, volcanic eruption)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P3 Particle Model",
    "question": "Draw a particle diagram for a liquid",
    "id": "31e8f848-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "What does the term “homozygous” mean?",
    "id": "36be5b9c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The individual has two identical alleles for this gene."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "What is the potential difference of mains electricity in the UK?",
    "id": "2e20ccf4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "230V"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "State one difference between the effects of hormones compared to the nervous system.",
    "id": "342e1f70-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Hormonal effects are slower/last longer"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C2 Bonding, Structure & the Properties of Matter",
    "question": "Explain why metals can conduct electricity",
    "id": "29844dba-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Delocalised electrons are free to carry charge"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Which focus knob should be used during low and medium power magnification?",
    "id": "1e4e427a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Coarse focus knob"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "State the equation which links acceleration, change in velocity and time taken",
    "id": "29cceeda-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "a=_v/t"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Suggest a source of carbon dioxide release.",
    "id": "3e4828de-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Burning fossil fuels/Deforestation/Peat destruction etc."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Name a source of air pollution.",
    "id": "3e14270a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Combustion of fossil fuels"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "In terms of electrons, what do group 0 elements have in common?",
    "id": "1fb96482-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Full outer shell"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "How do you make a soluble salt from an acid?",
    "id": "30b30ef0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "React the acid with a base. E.g. to make copper sulphate react copper oxide with sulphuric acid"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "State two benefits of genetic engineering.",
    "id": "380d386a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Improved growth rates/Increased yield/Increased food quality/Produce human proteins/enzymes as medicine"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "Name the type of models that are used to show how different organisms are related.",
    "id": "3959e952-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Evolutionary trees"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "Name the reagent used to test for starch.",
    "id": "24c8f47e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Iodine"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "State the equation which links distance, speed and time",
    "id": "29ca6980-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "s=vt"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C5 Energy Changes",
    "question": "What is a reaction profile?",
    "id": "31971b9a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A diagram which shows whether the reactants have more or less energy than the products."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "What is a hypotonic solution?",
    "id": "1eda33fc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A solution with a lower solute conc than the cell"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C1 Atomic Structure & The Periodic Table",
    "question": "What are groups in the periodic table?",
    "id": "1f97705c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The columns, numbered 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 0"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "What is type 1 diabetes?",
    "id": "343edbe4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Condition where pancreas does not make enough/any insulin"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P5 Forces",
    "question": "State the equation which links mass, momentum and velocity",
    "id": "29d1b398-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "p = mv"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "Define contamination",
    "id": "351910ac-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The unwanted presence of materials containing radioactive atoms"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "Define activity",
    "id": "350fa2b0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Rate at which decay occurs"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Name two ways in which organic material is returned to the soil for decomposers to break down.",
    "id": "3cdc0858-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Death + Excretion"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P2 Electricity",
    "question": "Draw the I-V characteristic for a filament lamp see",
    "id": "2e07e7a2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "teacher to draw on board…"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "What are some advantages of solar power?",
    "id": "2286dc08-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "No carbon dioxide produced"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B5 Homeostasis & response",
    "question": "Which two female hormones does the pituitary gland secretes during the menstrual cycle?",
    "id": "34765e7a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "FSH and LH"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "Suggest two diseases that may be treated with stem cell treatment.",
    "id": "1f4fe5de-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Paralysis, diabetes, blindness"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "Define irradiation",
    "id": "351b8ad0-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "When an object is exposed to radiation"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "What causes eutrophication?",
    "id": "3e0a7c00-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Fertilisers leaked into lakes, excess nutrients causes excessive plant growth, leading to an increase in competition/algae covering water surface (less light allowed into lake for water plants)"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "How do we calculate the total magnification of a microscope?",
    "id": "1e35b106-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Eyepiece lens x Objective lens magnifying power"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "How do ionising radiation causes mutation?",
    "id": "27fdecbc-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Penetrates cells and damage chromosomes"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P1 Energy",
    "question": "List 4 renewable energy resources.",
    "id": "2266b4b4-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Any 4 from: biofuel, wind, hydroelectricity, geothermal, tidal, wave, solar."
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B1 Cells",
    "question": "State the equation that links magnification, image size and actual size.",
    "id": "1e419e08-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Image Size = Actual Size x Magnification"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P4 Atomic Structure",
    "question": "What is the ionising power of beta radiation?",
    "id": "3669396e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "medium"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "State three causes of extinction.",
    "id": "3822b97e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "New predators; New diseases/pathogens; New/sucessful competitors"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C4 Chemical Changes",
    "question": "Define oxidation in the context of loss and gain of electrons",
    "id": "307a4f70-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Oxidation is the loss of electrons"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "What is a general formula?",
    "id": "396c9c0a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A mathematical formula which allows you to work out the chemical formula of a substance"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C3 Quantitative Chemistry",
    "question": "What is relative formula mass?",
    "id": "2cf065e2-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "The sum of the relative masses of each atom in a compound"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B2 Organisation",
    "question": "How does the hydrochloric acid in the stomach help with digestion?",
    "id": "2528575c-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Provides optimum pH  for pepsin to digest proteins"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B6 Inheritance, Variation & Evolution",
    "question": "How are gametes formed?",
    "id": "367e589e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Meiosis"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C7 Organic Chemistry",
    "question": "What are alkenes",
    "id": "399b596e-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "A different type of hydrocarbon which is more reactive than an alkane"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "C9 Chemistry of the Atmosphere",
    "question": "By what process do algae and plants produce oxygen?",
    "id": "3eca6e66-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "Photosynthesis"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "P6 waves",
    "question": "Which two angles are equal in reflection",
    "id": "3af5332a-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "angle of incidence and angle of reflection"
  },
  {
    "chapter": "B7 Ecology",
    "question": "Name two major impacts deforestation and peat destruction have on the environment and our biodiversity.",
    "id": "3e40a582-f0fa-11e9-af8e-28cfe91277a7",
    "answer": "More CO~2~ release (more global warming and acid rain) + Decrease biodiversity"
  }
]
